<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober reply to the sober answer of Reverend Mr. Cawdrey, to A serious question propounded viz. whether the ministers of England are bound by the word of God to baptise the children of all such parents, which say they believe in Jesus Christ, but are grosly ignorant, scandalous in their conversations, scoffers at godliness, and refuse to submit to church dicipline ... : also, the question of Reverend Mr. Hooker concerning the baptisme of infants : with a post-script to Reverend Mr. Blake / by G.I. Firmin ...</title>
            <author>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16401</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12009686</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12009686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41334)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 867:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober reply to the sober answer of Reverend Mr. Cawdrey, to A serious question propounded viz. whether the ministers of England are bound by the word of God to baptise the children of all such parents, which say they believe in Jesus Christ, but are grosly ignorant, scandalous in their conversations, scoffers at godliness, and refuse to submit to church dicipline ... : also, the question of Reverend Mr. Hooker concerning the baptisme of infants : with a post-script to Reverend Mr. Blake / by G.I. Firmin ...</title>
                  <author>Firmin, Giles, 1614-1697.</author>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647. Covenant of grace opened.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 57 [i.e. 59], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. :</publisher>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by Robert Littlebury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664. --  Sober answer to A serious question propounded by Mr. G. Firmin.</term>
               <term>Blake, Thomas, 1597?-1657. --  Vindiciae foederis.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52370:1"/>
            <p>A SOBER REPLY TO THE SOBER ANSWER OF REVEREND M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. CAWDREY, To a ſerious Queſtion propounded, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are bound by the Word of God to baptiſe the Children of all ſuch Parents, which ſay they believe in Jeſus Christ, but are groſly Ignorant, Scandalous in their Gonverſations, Scoffers at Godlineſs, and refuſe to ſubmit to Church-Diſcipline?</p>
            <p>The Affirmative is not ſufficiently cleared.</p>
            <p>ALSO, The Queſtion of Reverend Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> concerning the Baptiſme of Infants, of Parents <hi>non-Confederate</hi> is cleared, and it may ſerve for an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Cawdrey's Diatribe,</hi> with him upon the queſtion.</p>
            <p>With <hi>A Poſt-Script</hi> to Reverend Mr. <hi>Blake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By GI: FIRMIN <hi>Minister to the Church in</hi> Shalford.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB 6.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Teach me and I will hold my Tongue, and cauſe me to underſtand wherein I have erred.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprimatur <hi>JOS: CARYLL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> J. G. <hi>and are to be ſold by</hi> Robert Littlebury <hi>at the</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn <hi>in</hi> Little-Brittaine, <hi>1653.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52370:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> THE CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RTEO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Searcher of hearts knoweth with how little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I appeare in this Controverſie, and what little content I have in refuſing to baptiſe the children of ſuch as the queſtion mentions: it would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a man of a more holy ſpirit (as well as ſtronger parts) becauſe it pleades for purity of an Ordinance: but for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure heart to plead for a pure Ordinance is a moſt loathſome thing. Had not ſuch perſons as the queſtion mentions, pleaded the examples of other Ministers as their ſtrongeſt ground, (telling me that other Miniſters laughed at me for my practiſe) and alſo publikely oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me when I had dealt with them lovingly in private before, I had never appeared in print, which I did with an eager deſire of ſatisfaction, ſuppoſing that Miniſters would not laugh at others, unleſſe they had ſtrong grounds for their owne practiſe, which now I hoped to ſee: the practiſe being not mine alone (for then I had juſtly deſerved blame) but of many others before me who baptiſe not all.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> who hath pleaſed to undertake the anſwer [for which I really thank him] I ſaw not his piece againſt Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> till I had printed; but now I have read over that <hi>Diatribe</hi> and his anſwer to me, I confeſſe I am ſtill unſatisfied: yet ſmall matters would carry me to that which my owne will chooſeth moſt readily (God is my mitneſſe I have no ſiniſter reſpect in my practiſe) and which would be to my advantage in ſeverall respects if I might baptiſe all.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52370:3"/>
            <p>I was ſomewhat aſhamed to ſee ſo holy and able a mans as Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> to be joyned with me by Mr. <hi>Cawdrey:</hi> if the neereneſs of a holy man will ſhame one, what will the neereneſſe of a holy God doe? But ſince Providence hath done it, I did a little more ſeriouſly conſider of Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> queſtion, though different from mine, and I hope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have ſo cleared Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> out of himſelfe, that it will give content to the Reader. If I write againſt the Truth, Chriſt will, and I deſire he would blaſt it.</p>
            <p>The Reader may perceive by the mentioning of that eminent man of God Mr. <hi>Daniel Roger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> of <hi>Wetherfield,</hi> that this Treatiſe was finiſhed before his Death, and I ſent this Reply to him to view over; he ſent me them back with this Letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deare Couſin</hi> Firmin, <hi>I have ſent you both your Books againe, I have read them over and ſee nothing wherein you fail in anſwer to Mr.</hi> Cawdrey: <hi>But I confeſſe my thoughts are not ſo throughly heat, as yours are, to weigh all circumſtances, and paſſages of difference between you and him: its onely the concernment of ſuch as are</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>But as for further fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Mr.</hi> Cawdrey, <hi>you doe well to tell him you will hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth</hi> manum de tabula, <hi>and I pray hold your minde: if of reading Books, then ſurely of writing ſuch as theſe, there will be no end. I ſuppoſe your haſt of printing hath made you thinke long; I doubt not but you have ſufficiently proved, that your Arguments are not ſo weak, as your adverſary in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull conceit hath imputed to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, DANIEL ROGERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52370:3"/>
            <head>A SOBER REPLY TO A SOBER ANSVVER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Baptiſme were a means of Regeneration, as is the Preaching of the Word, then I ſhould not dare to refuſe the Baptizing of any perſon, what ever: or if Baptiſme were ſo neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that all thoſe Children which are Baptized, and die in their Infancy ſhall be ſaved, and thoſe which are not Baptized, and die in their Infancy ſhall periſh [as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmes (I think) ten times in one Epiſtle] then Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> did juſtly taxe me with rigidneſſe [as be doth P. 28. and if he had ſaid worſe I ſhould have ſubmitted] for non-admitting of ſome Children to Baptiſme. But neither the firſt<note n="(a)" place="margin">Walae. To. <hi>1. p. 85.</hi> &amp; <hi>491.</hi> Syney. pu. th diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>44. th. 27.28.</hi>
               </note> nor the ſecond<note n="(b)" place="margin">Chamier. To. <hi>4</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> Bell. Ezerv. To <hi>3</hi> d. <hi>2. c. 1.</hi>
               </note> doe our Orthodox Divines affirme. Baptiſme then being not appointed to bring perſons into union with Chriſt, but ſuppoſe union, or to bring perſons into the Covenant, but ſuppoſe a perſon already within the Covenant, being a Scale of it, and of all thoſe glorious priviledges contained in the Covenant, certainly this is not an Ordinance that is lightly to be regarded, [nor ſhall be I am confident when Chriſt comes to reforme his Church indeed] but thoſe who doe Adminiſter this (being ſtewards of it) had need looke to whom they give out this ſacred priviledge. Had God tied up Miniſters ſo, that we ſhould adminiſter it onely to reall Believers, then we had a hard taske. he hath left us a greater latitude, but whether ſuch a latitude as now the queſtion mentions, is that we are ſearching out. Reverend Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> hath yeelded P. 16. <hi>That ſuch a perſon as the queſtion mentions is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently qualified to be a Church member.</hi> Alſo P. 17. he ſaith thus, <hi>when we ſay a Profeſſion of the Faith is ſufficient to qualifie a Man to be made or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52370:4"/>continued a Member: we do not meane a bare profeſſion with his mouth, that be believes in</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>though viſibly he lives like an infidell: but thus at leaſt, when nothing in his life appeares to the contrary, though there be yet no great poſitive ſignes of his holineſſe.</hi> Let there be <hi>little</hi> poſitive ſignes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to a competent meaſure of Knowledge, and Converſation as you ſay, and we ſhall agree in that point. Alſo in his <hi>Review</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> P. 89. he affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meth; That, <hi>wicked Men are no fit materialls of a viſible Church.</hi>
               <q>And p. 94. 95. he moves a queſtion becauſe it is hard to judge of the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimum quod ſic</hi> of Knowledge or Holineſſe to make a man a fit matter of a Church, whether it were not ſafer for the Church to proceed by <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egations</hi> at her then <hi>Affirmation:</hi>
               </q> That is, <hi>in admitting or allowing of members, there is nothing appears to the contrary, but that the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty they have ſo much of ſaving Knowledge, and ſo faire a converſation in holineſſe, as may conſiſt with true grace?</hi> This is very faire, and certainly there will be ſome <hi>little</hi> poſitive ſignes in ſuch a perſon, and you may admit him by <hi>affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> hath fully confirmed me in that which is the ground of my ſcruple, for when I obſerved divers perſons came to demand Baptiſme of me, for their children, and I found them groſſely ignorant in the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary points of Salvation, and farre from underſtanding the nature of the Sacrament, and alſo when their converſation was proved by witneſſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcandalous, and far from what Mr. <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath ſet down, I queſtioned whether I was bound to give away ſuch a ſeale as this, and did therefore lovingly requeſt them to forbear a little, and lay in for more knowledge (offering to helpe them) and ſo to labour to reforme their ſcandalous converſations, then I would doe it.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Cawdry</hi> condemns my practiſe,<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> and tells the World I have confuted my Opinion and my Practiſe, and while I goe about to prove the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> I have concluded the <hi>Affimative:</hi> and that is by one ſentence which I have affirmed, <hi>viz. So long as wicked perſons are telerated they may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge,</hi> &amp;c. [what my ſentence is I ſhall preſently give it you plainely.] <hi>This ſentence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>confutes (as it contradicts) both his Queſtion and his Practice, and it unto gives us an anſwer to all his Arguments.</hi> You have ſaid enough; He ſaith in the ſame Page that I have <hi>three times at leaſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that Propoſition:</hi> what I have affirmed I will owne, there is a fourth place where I have ſaid the ſame words in P. 41. 4. 2. (it ſhould be, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are falſe printed) <q>
                  <hi>That ſuch perſons as are ignorant and ſcandalous, if they be owned for Church members, they have a remote right to Baptiſme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and to the Lords Supper, you muſt not deny it,</hi>
               </q> by theſe words, <hi>you muſt not deny it;</hi> I ſuppoſe you do not underſtand me, <hi>you muſt not deny ſuch the Lords Supper,</hi> that is far from my thoughts, for then I ſhould condemne our old holy Divines and others now, who alone will keepe back, it may be halfe their Pariſh from the Lords Supper, I condemne them not at all, but thinke they have done well,<note place="margin">As you ſay Review Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> p. 94.</note> though you ſcarce think ſo by your paſſage. P. 21. that then is the meaning of it, <hi>You muſt not deny it, but they have a Remote Right to the one as well as to the other.</hi> But I ſuppoſe you well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52370:4"/>my minde, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no more there there th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, which now I ſhall conſider in may Booke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there you ſay I have it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies, once from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> giving of title to Circumciſion ſo long as Church members. For the <hi>Iewes</hi> I ſhall ſay this once for all: if you can prove unto me that the grounds of the <hi>Iewes</hi> adminiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Circumciſion were onely the ſame and no other of our adminiſtring Baptiſme, then I ſhall be very much ſwayed with Arguments you draw from them: but if there were ſomething peculiar to them as being <hi>ſuch a Seed, and ſuch a Church,</hi> (which I doe verily believe, and ſhall ſpeake to afterwards) then what Arguments you draw from them (excepting this, that as God made a Covenant with believing <hi>Abrabam,</hi> and gave him the Scale, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his Children, (being reputed believers with their believing Father) ſo the believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed have right to the Scale of Baptiſme for themſelves and their children, which I ſee confirmed in the Goſpe I do very little regard.</p>
            <p>You mention the ſame Page againe e it is true ſir, there I have ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> down my minde plainly, and that I will ſtand to. There was a queſtion moved, <hi>whether ſuch a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> profeſſion (as the caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which I ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed mentions) with groſſe ignorence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were ſufficient to make and continue a Man a Church-member!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I ſaid ſuppoſe that our Divines, who Baptize all goe upon this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all perſons in <hi>England</hi> do profeſſe they believe in Chriſt, hence all are Church members, <hi>Ergo</hi> all are Baptized.</q>
            </p>
            <p>My anſwer to this was thus: <q>
                  <hi>This I confeſs as ſome diſadvantage to me,</hi> [Mr. <hi>Cawdry</hi> might have ſhowen me ſo much favour as to let his Reader know, that what ſtrength he hath againſt me, I gave it him knowingly, but he never mentions that I ſaw the difficulty, though I have expreſſed it, but triumphs over me, as if what I had ſaid was unawares, but I looke for no favour as his hand.] <hi>For if a Man be looked upon as a viſible Saint, and reputed a Member of is true Church, if that Member be very ſcandalous, and the Church let him alone, and not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le with him, that perſon may challenge any Ordinance in the Church, both Baptiſme and the Lords Supper:</hi>
               </q> This I have ſaid and will not recall, make of it what you can't and here you have my minde fully, with the next words adjoyned, which I will rehearſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</p>
            <p>From this you have drawn up a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yllogiſme to ſhew the World,<note place="margin">Page 15.</note> how I have Confuted and Comtradicted my ſelfe, and thus you have caſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Child of a ſandalous Member tolerated, may be Baptized. But the Child of a ſcandalous Member not Excommunicated, is the Child of a ſcandalous Member tolerated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo, <hi>it may be Baptized, and is Miniſter may lawfully Baptize i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have killed me with my own Weapon, but ſir when I looke on your Syllogiſme, it comes at firſt view as if you muſt out off one of the ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of it, for I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on foure: I pray wheat was this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>me,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52370:5"/>
               <hi>and a Miniſter may lawfully</hi> [that is, the word binds him to it, which is the pinch of the Queſtion] <hi>Baptize is,</hi> diſpoſed in the premiſſes? if you ſay, <hi>it was included in the</hi> Major, <hi>when I ſaid it may be Baptized.</hi> Sir I cannot tell that, if a Miniſter will admit a Man into the Church as a Member, though the Man be not qualified as you have told us Members muſt be, but very ſcandalous in converſation, and groſly ignorant, yet the Miniſter thinkes he have enough to admit him a Member, and conſequently hee Baptizeth him; Such a Miniſter <hi>may Baptize</hi> him if he will, he may ſay, <hi>(A Member admitted may be Baptized, but this is a Member admitted)</hi> But the word doth not binde him, no, he prophanes the Ordinace, though he will admit him a Member.</p>
            <p>However Sir you ſhould have expreſſed this in the <hi>Major,</hi> as you have done in the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> then your <hi>Major</hi> I would have denyed; you will ſay to me, the <hi>Major is my one propoſition, and upon that I argue, and ſhow you and the World how you have confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed your ſelfe.</hi> No Sir I do utterly deny it; ſhew me ſuch a paſſage where I have ſaid that <hi>Scandalous Members</hi> [ſuch us our Engliſh perſons are, named in the Queſtion] <hi>tollerated, may have their Children Baptized, and the word bindes Miniſters to do it.</hi> Shew your Reader that, and then you ſay ſomething: but how farre I was from thinking or ſpeaking ſo, the very next words unto that which you ſay is my ſentence, and out of which I have conſuted my ſelfe, do declare: my words are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But I conceive ſuch a perſon is not ſufficiently qualified to make a Member of a Church, nor ought to be continued a Member of the Church: but the Church ought to ſeeke to reforme him, or if not, to caſt him out, ſo that if the Church will let ſuch a perſon alone, and give him theſe Ordinances, there will be guilt charged upon that Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This ſentence I conceive (if the Reader be but indifferent, and not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced againſt me) will ſave me from <hi>ſelfe-confutation:</hi> if the ſentence be not true, but Mr. <hi>Cawdry</hi> had proved that the Miniſter is not too blame though he lets him alone, and yet may <hi>lawfully</hi> Baptize. Then had he ſpoken to my ſcruple indeed, and I would have thanked him heartily, but then I had not confuted my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But ſtill Mr. <hi>Caw.</hi> will urge from my owne words, thus I have ſaid, <hi>Scandalom Members, if tolerated, let alone by the Church, they have a remote right to Baptiſme and the Supper;</hi> Ergo, <hi>they may lawfully have their Children Baptized, and the word binds Miniſters to do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſhall anſwer, firſt to the Antecedent, then to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.</p>
            <p>To the Antecedent I anſwer, firſt [according to our Congregationall Principles] that which gives a Man the <hi>firſt right</hi> to a Sacrament, viz. <hi>his intereſt in the Covenans of the Goſpel</hi> [which you uſe very much againſt Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> taking the words from himſelfe] this Man hath not: for he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth viſibly declare to the Churches that he hath no intereſt in that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52370:5"/>and your ſelfe deny it not, by what you have affirmed concerning the qualifications of Church-members. So then he hath no right, in that reſpect, all the right he hath is by the toleration of the Church, which the Church had beſt looke to, now I do confeſſe that <hi>firſt right</hi> is the maine in my eſteeme, though not <hi>all</hi> that is required: as in a Miniſter, the great matter is the qualification of the perſon, which is his inward call, yet it is not all, but his Ordination is alſo requiſite: but if Biſhops, or Presbyters ſhould ordaine a ſcandalous and ignorant ſot, not able to teach himſelfe, nor the Church, I ſhould extreamely doubt of ſuch a Miniſter: ſo here I conceive this <hi>firſt right</hi> is the chiefe, but yet as Mr. <hi>Hoolter</hi> ſaith <hi>Baptiſme he muſt come by in a right Order,</hi> i.e. <hi>he muſt be a Member of ſome congregation;</hi> and not an <hi>individuum vagum,</hi> belonging to no particular Congregation, nor any body to have inſpection over him. But if Miniſters will admit perſons that have not this <hi>firſt right,</hi> and continue ſuch amongſt them, here indeed is a kinde of right, but this let the Miniſters look to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I anſwer according to your Principles: you make a <hi>Mans Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>alone, without his joyning of himſelfe to any congregation, to be that which gives him right,</hi> and you oppoſe Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Divines for requiring that joyning to any particular Church before they will Baptize: thus you ſay; <hi>All Children of Chriſtians, as Chriſtians have ſuch right</hi> to Baptiſme, and in the ſame Page,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatri.</hi> p. 186.</note> 
               <hi>All Children of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as ſuch, have right to Baptiſme.</hi> Thus in your anſwer to me P. 12. you ſay, <hi>a perſon Excommunicated gives right to his childs Baptiſme, becauſe for ſtate be is a Chriſtian, and retains his Baptiſme.</hi> Now Sir I hope you meane it muſt be ſuch Chriſtianity as your ſelfe have ſaid is fit to make a Church-member [I hope you do not meane ſuch Chriſtianity as our queſtion ſpeakes of] by vertue of that ſay you he is a Member of the Catholike-church. Now Sir if that <hi>onely</hi> gives a Man right and his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and yet a Man have not <hi>that,</hi> I can ſee no right he hath at all, it ſeemes ſtrange to me that Men ſhould be Members of a particular Church and not of the Catholike-Church, of the latter theſe are not Members, for they have not ſo much as ſhould give them a right to that Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if you will hold to what you have ſaid about the qualifications of the matter of a Church: for only ſuch Chriſtianity makes Men Members of the Catholike-church, which theſe fall very ſhort of. We uſe to unwinde a bottome the ſame way we wound it, if you will winde the bottome thus, <hi>a Profeſſor, or Believer (ſuch a one as you ſay is fitly qualified)</hi> as ſuch, <hi>have by vertus of his profeſſion</hi> onely, <hi>a right to his own and Childs Baptiſme,</hi> then I unwinde it the ſame way, <hi>he that is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Profeſſour as you mention, hath no right at all.</hi> Such are thoſe our Caſe ſpeakes of.</p>
            <p>Now Sir here lay my trouble, that ſince theſe perſons in the firſt and maine reſpect have no right, but what they have is onely by my tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this queſtion aroſe; whether in the beginnings of Reformation [wherein as <hi>Innius</hi> ſaith, ſomething will be extraordinary] the perſons being numerous, and not ſo fit it may be to Excommunicate in regard of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52370:6"/>number <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though in reſpect of their wilfull igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> nuing ſcandalous after admonitions, they deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not the Church ſuſpend ſuch from the Seal of the Cover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a for thus I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive while I firſt adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſh people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on their ignorance, and ſcandalous living,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suſpenſion is</hi> Excommunicatio Minor.</note> and they refuſing to heare me, I doe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e conſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Church ſuſpend I do not rol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but you ſpeak as if there were nothing oppoſite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Toleration, but Excommunication.</p>
            <p>Or thus, according to our Congregationall Principles; which maintain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Non-communion</hi> in caſe Excommunication cannot be exerciſed againſt a multitude; ſo I do here exclude them from ſuch Ordinances as doe hold forth Communion, and ſo it is Non commanion in effects. Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion or Separation in ſome caſes when there is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>de, the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yden Proſeſſort</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Synop. pur. Theol. dicp. <hi>48.</hi> Theſ. <hi>28.29.</hi>
               </note> maintaine.</p>
            <p>To the Conſequence I anſwer, by denying it, <hi>viz Miniſters are not bound by the word to Baptize all the Children of perſons groſly ignorant, and ſcandalous, though tolerated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſtill carry it in reference to <hi>England,</hi> where you ſay all are Chriſtians, and Church members: here now I ſhall ſpeaks more then I would have done, feeling the temptation of my Brethren in my own hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; but your triumphing over me, and celling the World, how I have at once confuted my ſelfe, makes me by way of diſcourſe to clear my ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, though I think it is done already. Thus then I argue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If ſuch Members as the queſtion ſpeakes of be continued ſuch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Argumant.</note>
               <hi>through the Miniſters negligence and contifulnce, then the word doth not bind Miniſters to give the Seal of the Covenant to their Children, but the Antecedent is true,</hi> Ergo, <hi>the conſequent is true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Antecedent I had rather have applied onely to my ſelfe, then any other Miniſters being far more holy then my ſelfe, I ſhould thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay ſelfe to have been guilty of connivance, but my queſtion, and Mr. <hi>Caw.</hi> (as I ſaid before) puts me upon this.</p>
            <p>If the Antecedent be denied, I prove it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When Miniſters have power put into their hands, whereby they may reforme if they will, and will not, then their Toleration comes from connivance; and ſo is ſinfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Miniſters have now power put into their hands, whereby they may reform if they will,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is cleare: for what power oppoſes? Church power there is none above the Miniſters; for the civill power that doth not oppoſe, but that power actually defends ſuch Miniſters, and Churches as doe reforme, and doe deny Baptiſme to ſuch ſcandalous ones; This favour once would have beene eſteemed very great: what ever we conceive of Toleration, as now it ſtands, yet this benefit we have by Toleration, that Miniſters need not Tolerate ſuch perſons if they will. <hi>It is an ill wind, blowes no body good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I perceive your Anſwer in P. 30: you tell us, <hi>of a Pope-like power
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52370:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a Miniſter doth uſurp, who alone ſhall reforme though by ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ention:</hi> you ſuppoſe others will charge us with it, but whether Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> will not ſay ſo alſo. I ſomewhat doubt, by obſerving this place and Page 20.21. I will not conclude ſo of him; but that he is againſt any Miniſter that ſhall doe ſo, that is cleare. By a <hi>Miniſter alone,</hi> if you meane thus, that a Miniſter alone without his people, or againſt the Chriſtians conſent ſhall ſuſpend, whom he pleaſe, indeed I doubt of ſuch a practiſe: but if the Members (viſible Believers) ſhall come and bring in witneſſe againſt perſons, and deſire to have them debarred, till they will amend, and thus they conſent to their Officer in ſuſpending. I know of no <hi>Pope-like</hi> power here uſuped.</p>
            <p>To this therefore I will anſwer further.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you and ten Miniſters more, or as many as you pleaſe, will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> together, and ſet up a <hi>Claſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> forme of Government [and then you conceive you have power] you may if you will, who hinders you? I know of no power that oppoſe you. Therefore this is not a ſufficient P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your meaning (in good earneſt) to deny to a particular <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Church, a power to reform its own Members (as you ſeeme to expreſſe) in that manner I have ſet downe? I hope we ſhall finde divers Claſſicall Divines of another Opinion: I pray what is your meaning, when you ſay; <hi>As for Reverend and Learned</hi> Whitaker, <hi>whoſe Teſtimony he makes uſe of</hi> P. 52. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as he grants but what w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Review Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> p. 111.</note> 
               <hi>that every particular Church hath a power owen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> own Members,</hi> what power you meane is plaine by the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> and learned <hi>Whitaker</hi> M. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> writes himſelfe, <hi>Paſtor of the Church at Billing;</hi> Now I pray give me a reaſon why ſo godly and able a Paſtor with his Church ſhould not have power over his own Members, unleſſe he will contradict himſelfe (as he ſaith, I doe) but I hope you doe not meane, there is no particular Church, but a Claſſicall Church, for that appoſeth what before you have ſaid of your ſelfe: our <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> runnes 14 miles in length, and 20 ſeverall Pariſhes in it, to make all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> particular Church, is very hard, but if the Church at <hi>Billing</hi> have power over its own members, why may not the Church at <hi>Shalford</hi> have the ſame power?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Would you have <hi>Ruling Elders</hi> to joyne with me? I obſerve divers <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of the <hi>Claſſicall</hi> Divines queſtion, whether there be any ſuch Officer diſtinct from the Preaching Elder. But though I have not Elders actually ordained [I perceive alſo here you doe not ordaine your Elders, which is ſtrange, if Deacons were] yet I have thoſe whom I looke upon to be Elders, and without whom I do nothing that concerns Diſcipline. That which hath hindred us, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uncertainty of my maintenance, being cut off from a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> put which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, from a Sequeſtration, when I was firſt called; The maintenance their if from the place being not ſufficient to maintaine my charge, I am uncertaine of my abode here.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When I was ordained by the <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sbytery,</hi> I thought I had the power <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52370:7"/>of a Paſtour conveyed to me: now one part is to <hi>Rule,</hi> I thinke, but to ſay I cannot put forth that power alone, but I muſt have more Elders to joyne with before I can doe any thing; I deſire to ſee a Scripture for that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Diſcipline was carried on by more then one in the Examples we have in the Scripture, there being more then one Officer in thoſe Churches, muſt this needs conclude; Therefore the power of a Paſtour muſt lie dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, if he have no other Elders to joyne with him, though his people doe as I ſaid before, I ſhould deny this conſequence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Suppoſe I ſtay till the <hi>Claſſis</hi> be formed and Act, ſhall wee have power then to reform? But ſuppoſe my people aske other Miniſters of the <hi>Claſſis</hi> beſides my ſelfe, what power they have to reforme them, who made them Rulers over the people againſt their wills and conſent, having called none but <hi>my ſelf</hi> for their Paſtour? you muſt have a call you ſay to put forth your power <hi>actu ſecundo,</hi> in another Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Suppoſe there were a Church on an Iſland, where there was onely a Paſtour, ſhould he and his people be denyed to reforme, ſince there is no other Church neere him? if you will give him power, I pray give me, for it is all one to be on an <hi>Iſland,</hi> where there are no more Churches that <hi>can</hi> combine, and ſo helpe one another, as to be in another place where are thouſands, but none <hi>will:</hi> it is <hi>cannot</hi> there, it is <hi>will not</hi> heare. Yet Sir, there is a Congregationall Church in the next Towne, and when need is I ſeeke counſell of that reverend Officer Mr. <hi>Dan Rogers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could ſay more, but I forbeare. What you ſay concerning Mr. <hi>Icanes,</hi> I have not ſeene that worthy Mans labours, for I live in an obſcure Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage remote from <hi>London,</hi> and ſeldome heare of Bookes, neither will my meanes allow me to buy all Bookes that come out. But Sir, I take your Opinion, for you ſay in your Epiſtle, <hi>it is hard to judge, whether his way or mine be the beſt, or worſt way of Cure.</hi> Now if it be <hi>hard to ſay,</hi> then <hi>I</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you are not clear your ſelfe, for what he hath writ.</p>
            <p>So much for the Antecedent; now I come to the Conſequence. <hi>viz. If it be connivance and negligence that is the cauſe of this Toleration</hi> [which I doubt is true in many] <hi>then the word doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bind me, or I may not lawfully Baptize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ſinfull admiſſions will not juſtifie a Miniſter in adminiſtring the Ordinance of Baptiſme, then neither will ſinfull Tolerations juſtifie a Miniſter in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Antecedens is true,</hi> Ergo, <hi>the conſequent is true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinfull admiſſions will not:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro. rod.</hi> p. 515.</note> learned <hi>Gilleſpy ſaith: no Conſciencious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter would adventure to Baptize one, who hath manifeſt and infallible ſignes of unregeneration, we cannot be anſwerable to God if we ſhould.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo he ſaith,<note place="margin">Page 544.</note> 
               <hi>it were a prophanation of Baptiſmel, to Baptize</hi> a Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene, <hi>being manifeſtly under the power of abominable finnes, although he could give a ſound, and Orthodox confeſſion of Faith.</hi> This is more then thouſands of the Church members of <hi>England</hi> can doe, and yet live under the power of ſinnes bad enough. His grounds I have quoted before
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52370:7"/>with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and the Schoolemen, <hi>Aquinas, Durandus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serious Queſt.</hi> p. 21, 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>Greg. de Val.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the conſequence, if it be ſaid, <hi>there is more required in one who is a Member, he muſt firſt be caſt out:</hi> this takes not off the force of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the perſon is ſinfully tolerated, as well at firſt ſinfully admitted; as he might have beene and ſhould have beene denyed admiſſion, and ſo the Ordinance had been ſaved, ſo this perſon may and ought to be dealt with (there being now power in the hands of Miniſters) ſo the Ordinance is ſaved, ſinfull admiſſion cauſed the Ordinance at firſt to be prophaned, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full toleration cauſe it now to be prophaned.</p>
            <p>If you would turne me off here (as you doe afterward) by telling me <hi>the Argument ſhould proceed of the ſame perſon, which it doth not, the Child and the Parent are different perſons.</hi> Sir, this will not ſerve the turne, my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument proceeds upon one and the ſame Title, the Parents Title is the Childs Title, the Child hath no other Title, nor pleads any other but the Parents Title, the Parent expreſſes his Title for himſelfe, and his Child being a branch of that ſtock; if the child pleaded a Title diſtinct from the Parents, as a Title of its own, then my Argument were fallacious [as I ſhall charge you anon] but if the child could ſpeake, it could plead only this, <hi>my Parent is within the Covenant, the Covenant is made with the Believing Parent, and his or her ſeed; Therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>give me the Scale: by vertue of him, or her it is made with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You tell me afterward. P. 25. <hi>I may Baptize the Child of the prophaneſt Man in</hi> England, <hi>as of the godli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> [my Argument tends to that] <hi>Man; only you would have me grieve that I cannot reform this abuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence I obſerve. Firſt, this ordinance may be abuſed. Secondly, <hi>de Facto</hi> it is abuſed in this adminiſtration to ſuch vile perſons; only ſay you his ſaves all, <hi>you have no power to reform this Abuſe, and for that I much grieve;</hi> but this I deny, I have power, and ſo have you and many more, but by you I cannot conceive the Ordinance is abuſed, for if the word bindes me to give ſuch a perſon the Ordinance; I know not how I abuſe it in following of the command of the word, ſo that I have no ſuch cauſe to grieve in reſpect of the adminiſtring of the Ordinance, for that is well enough, while ſuch a one is tolerated; I am bound to do it [that is our Queſtion] ſay you, the griefe muſt be in regard of the Mans toleration in the Church. But Sir, remember one thing more, you tell us <hi>though ſuch a perſon be Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, yet becauſe be is a Chriſtian, and retaines his Baptiſme;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 12.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore the Miniſter muſt Baptize his Child:</hi> what cauſe of grieving is there now, for what power is there beyond Excommunication? ſo that you do but deceive us in talking of Reformation.</p>
            <p>If Toleration, though ſinfull, will ſave us from prophaning of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, then Miniſters may take their eaſe as to that point, and let all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and vile Members alone, let them partake of both Seals, for ſo long as tolerated, the word binds you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o give them Baptiſme, and the Supper, and the word doth not binde me to prophane an Ordinance.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52370:8"/>
            <p>So much for my firſt Argument.<note place="margin">2. Argument.</note> I come to a ſecond Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> to prove, though ſcandalous Members in <hi>England</hi> are tolerated, and by vertue of that Toleration they will challenge any Ordinance, yet the word binds not me to give.</p>
            <p>If ſo, <hi>then the Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>are bound to adminiſter the Lords Supper to the groſſeſt ignorant perſons, horribly ſcandalous, Ranters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Conſequent is falſe;</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Antecedent is falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſequence is cleare, they are Church-members tolerated, ſaith Mr. <hi>Caw.</hi> we have no power to helpe; Therefore they may by vertue of that Principle, by which he hath me on the hip, as he thinks.</p>
            <p>I thinke Sir you ſpeake the ſame words,<note place="margin">P. 94.</note> 
               <hi>in Review of</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſcandalous Men, tolerated in a Church, whilest tolerated they are Members to all Ordinances for themſelves, and their poſteritie.</hi> Then all the Ranters, &amp;c. are members to the Lords Supper, and you have no power, you ſay to helpe it. Yet I preſume you would ſinde power before you would admit all ſuch to the Supper.</p>
            <p>This I would ſaine have cleared to me, that the Officers are bound to looke to the Members more in admitting them to the Supper then to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: and the Supper, reſpect both the ſame Covenant, there is but one condition [whether there be <hi>Conditio propri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicta</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Twiſſ.</hi> Vind. grapraefa. <hi>Sect. 8.</hi>
               </note> in the Covenant of grace is another queſtion] of the coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll of grace, <hi>viz.</hi> That man then, who can rightly take a Seale, or Convey a Seale of this Covenant to his, muſt viſibly appeare to have the condition of the Covenant, [which is the firſt and maine right,<note place="margin">Ames <hi>Medal.</hi> Th. c. 24. Th. 19. Rhaetorſ.<hi>Exar. Apol.</hi> p. 313.</note>] if he do ſo appeare, and therefore can convey the Seale to his Child, why he may not have the other Seale for himſelfe, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be a Believer, and alſo being in right Order for my part, I ſee no reaſon.</p>
            <p>I muſt not here condemne the holy Divines, who have before kept this Ordinance; neither dare <hi>I</hi> ſay the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> did very weakly, to trouble the <hi>Parliament</hi> in requeſting the Houſes to make an Act againſt ſuch perſons, that they might be debarred from the Lords Supper, which <hi>I</hi> muſt doe, if they were bound to give it while ſuch were tolerated Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they would finde hard worke to have Excommunicated all theſe. If any ſay <hi>I</hi> condemne the former Divines for Baptizing all: <hi>I</hi> pray let them ſay no more then they heare me ſay, <hi>I</hi> do not do ſo, onely <hi>I</hi> would gladly ſee the reaſon of the practiſe, and for thoſe, who lived before theſe times, <hi>I</hi> can anſwer my ſelfe another way.</p>
            <p>I pray remember my Queſtion, how it can be proved that the <hi>Officers</hi> muſt looke more to this Seale then the other. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. It is ſaid, <hi>Let a man examine himſelf, &amp;c.</hi> True, ſo he hath need before he comes to Baptiſme: but what is this to the Officers of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Lords Supper was adminiſtred every Lords Day in thoſe times, what muſt the Officers examine them every weeke? here is worke enough, they looked to them [or ſhould have done] when they firſt tooke them in to be Members, and ſo if they did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52370:8"/>not walke as ſuch ought to do, they were to looks after them, reforme, or caſt out, but in ſo doing they ſaved other Ordinances as well as this. But we have a notion taken up, as if Diſcipline were appointed onely to ſave the Lords Supper from being prophaned, and no other Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Will the 44 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 9 prove it? I pray prove that <hi>Sanctuary</hi> (there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) meanes only the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> that <hi>Sanctuary</hi> and <hi>Lords Supper</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe who interpret, they ought to prove their interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which you muſt clear to make your anſwer good, in P. 26.</p>
            <p>Will 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. prove it? <hi>Stewards must be faithfull, this muſt be only in the</hi> Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Will <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. prove it? <hi>Holy things muſt not be given to Dogs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bapt.</note>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> applies this Text to the Adminiſtration of Baptiſme, as well as to the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And if it muſt be at the firſt, then why not as well when it comes to be adminiſtred by vertue of one, who is a Dog. [The word <hi>I</hi> love not to uſe in reſpect of others, knowing my wicked heart] there may be many who are Church-members by reaſon of Toleration onely (and that To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration its doubted if it be not ſinful who yet are ſuch Dogs as that Text mentions, and upon this Notion Miniſters have before exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them from the Supper. Your ſelfe ſpeake to this purpoſe <hi>Diatar.</hi> Page 184.</p>
            <p n="3">3. One Argument more to prove, <hi>though ſuch may challenge by reaſon of my Toleration, yet I am not bound to give,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Argument.</note> and here <hi>I</hi> will give examples of of what <hi>I</hi> have found, and know concerning <hi>ignorance,</hi> then draw up my Argument.</p>
            <p>In my owne Pariſh, <hi>I</hi> was queſtioning with one about his eſtate, hee had lived long in <hi>Eſſex</hi> that which the Man builded upon was this, ſaid he, <hi>I have been no Drunkard, and I Repent.</hi> What it was to <hi>Repene?</hi> he could not tell: but then <hi>I</hi> enquired what knowledge he had of Chriſt; The Man <hi>I</hi> perceived knew nothing of him, but when <hi>I</hi> told him how Chriſt was <hi>God-man</hi> ſent to fulfill the Law, to die, to make ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice, and ſuch ordinary plaine things. The Man wondered to heare ſuch things, in ſo much indeed that <hi>I</hi> could not but wonder my ſelfe that a man ſhould live above 50 years in ſuch a place as <hi>Eſſex</hi> is, and not know theſe plaine things.</p>
            <p>Another was asked, what Chriſt was? the man could give him no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: to help him, he was asked againe, whether he were a God, or a Man? he anſwered plainely hee could not tell, but ſaid, <hi>he thought he was a Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is an Obſervation that <hi>I</hi> have made, [becauſe Mr. <hi>Gaw.</hi> ſayes <hi>we are all Chriſtians,</hi> P. 4.] when <hi>I</hi> have beene diſcourſing with people about their conditions, they will tell me ſtories of what they have not been, and ſome other ſilly matters, but for Chriſt, not one word of him, unleſſe when <hi>I</hi> have put it upon them; <hi>what is Chriſt nothing?</hi> then they will tell me, <hi>yes, they muſt believe in Chriſt,</hi> God forbid the contrary, but to know Chriſt, and what it is to believe in him, alas they are far ſhort of this. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52370:9"/>this is not onely my obſervation, but a godly Miniſter in <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> told mee the very ſame thing he obſerved in his Pariſh, not one word of Chriſt, till he put it into their minds, then having taken up Chriſt by <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> they muſt ſay ſomething.</p>
            <p>But for the Covenant of Grace (which Baptiſme reſpects alſo) that is the ſtrangeſt thing to people, they know not what it meanes.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Sin,</hi> people have a Tradition that there is that which people call <hi>Sin,</hi> but for themſelves to be guilty of any particular ſinne, <hi>I</hi> have beene forced to run over the Commandements, open them, and tell them how my ſelf have been guilty, and yet could I ſcarce convince ſome, they were guilty, only all are ſinnes, and ſo are they.</p>
            <p>A godly friend of mine told me he asked a Woman that was talking with him, what ſhee had for Heaven? ſhee anſwered him roundly, <hi>ſhe had never effended God in all her Life:</hi> yet ſhee was above 50 yeares of Age.</p>
            <p>Another told him, <hi>ſhe had kept all the Commandements:</hi> ſhee was not ſo old indeed, but he had much a doe to convince her, ſhe had broke one, yet theſe perſons lived where there had been excellent Preaching.</p>
            <p>Another comming to a neere friend of mine to have his Child Baptized, he asked him why he would have it Baptized? he anſwered, <hi>becauſe others had</hi> the asked him what good it would do his Child? he anſwered, <hi>As much as heretofore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another came to him, he asked him, how many Gods there were? he anſwered, <hi>Ten;</hi> ſuppoſing he miſtooke himſelfe, for the Commandements he asked him, how many Commandements there were? he anſwered <hi>Two,</hi> he asked him which was the firſt? he anſwered <hi>Salvation;</hi> the ſecond <hi>I</hi> know not what it was: the Man profeſſed he did anſwer as well as he could.</p>
            <p>I thinke you are not much better in <hi>Northhamptonſhire,</hi> for a godly Miniſter told me of one in his Pariſh, that had a Prayer, but <hi>I</hi> think there was never ſuch a one heard before, this ſentence was often repeated, <hi>And Jeſus was</hi> Her <hi>Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe inſtances have been ſince our Reformation began, and if Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhould ſearch all, certaintly we ſhould be amazed to heare the Anſwers.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, I apply this: you ſay all theſe are Church-Members tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, they can therefore challenge Baptiſme, and becauſe their Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on give them a <hi>Right,</hi> Therefore the word bindes me to Baptize their Childen. But Sir, may I not better put theſe off for a time untill by Catechizing of them, they come to underſtand Sinne, Chriſt, and the Covenant of Grace? the word ſaith, <hi>Teach and Baptize,</hi> yea ſay you, at the firſt conſtitution; but if we finde ſuch perſons as you call Members, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in conſtituted Churches that are ignorant in the knowledge of Sin, Covenant of Grace, yea and of Chriſt [ſave onely they have taken up ſuch a Name that there is one Chriſt, and the Nation receives him] as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52370:9"/>are the very Heathen, (nay for ſin, the Heathen know more) is there not as much and more reaſon to <hi>Teach</hi> theſe before I will <hi>Baptize</hi> by vertue of them, let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>Am I bound to Baptize a Child preſently ſo ſoon as it is brought? They make nothing to keepe Children a fortnight, a moneth, yea more (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as their occaſions are) before they will offer them to Baptiſme, may not I th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, finding the Parents unfit, delay if it be two moneths, till they are taught before I will Baptize? What is the danger, where is the Rule broken, where am I tyed to Baptize one ſo ſoone as offered, though never ſo unfit? the eight day that was ſet for Circumciſion, concernes not us, we can Baptize before if we will.</p>
            <p>So for Scandall, if uncleane perſons ſhall bring their Baſtards, the Ranters, or who you will, muſt <hi>I</hi> preſently Baptize, becauſe you ſay a Church member tolerated will challenge a right to the Ordinance? ſhall <hi>I</hi> not firſt require Repentance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> required <hi>Repentance:</hi> yea ſay you at firſt conſtitution, he and Apoſtles did. But Sir,<note place="margin">You know <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> minde, concerning A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, 2.1. <hi>De pudicitid.</hi> And <hi>Cyprian</hi> te's us it was the practiſe of ſome not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Ep.</hi> 52. <hi>Synop pur. Disp.</hi> 48. Tb. 31.</note> ſhall perſons now be as vile and worſe [for the continuance in the Church, aggravates their ignorance and ſcandall,] then at the firſt conſtitution, and ſhall I not now require Repentance of ſuch before I Baptize by vertue of them? yea, and that the Repentance may in judgement of Charity give hopes of a true Repentance: and if any will grant it for this one ſcandall; I know not but the ſame Rule will reach for other Scandalls.</p>
            <p>If you will Baptize all theſe ignorant ones, and the Scandalous ones without any more a doe, <hi>but to preſſe the Covenant</hi> [which they know not] <hi>on them,</hi> as you ſay, do if you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Head of <hi>Selfe confutation: I</hi> am not yet beaten off, but that paſſage of the <hi>Leyden Profeſſors,</hi> doe a little favour me, the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, <hi>whether if there be a great number in the Church, who off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in Doctrine of Life, may we now uſe Excommunication?</hi> The anſwer is, <hi>If men be openly and contumaciouſly corrupt, Let the multitude be great, yet to ſuch, godly Paſtours ought not, nor may give the</hi> Sacraments <hi>of Divine Grace, but with one conſent they muſt be denyed, and commit the event to God: becauſe godly Paſtours may not communicate the</hi> Signes <hi>of Grace to them, to whom Christ doth openly deny them, and forbids the Communicating of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I obſerve, they doe not ſtand for the Excommunication of a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, for theſe words <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Signes of Grace,</hi> if there be <hi>Enallage numeri,</hi> that they ſhould meane onely the Lords Supper. <hi>I</hi> ſhould marvell at it, that there ſhould be ſo much paines taken in ſolving of the queſtion, and then to come and tell us onely of <hi>Suſpenſion fromthe Supper,</hi> which is ſo common a thing.</p>
            <p>But for their reaſon I would make uſe of that, and when they have brought me the Scripturall ground, where Chriſt forbids the Miniſters to give the Parent one <hi>Signe of Grace,</hi> I will ſee if the ſame ground will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eny us to give the Child the other ſigne of Grace, by vertue of this Parent.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52370:10"/>
            <p>For your Pro-parent, and Adoption, that comes in to be confidered in another place, <hi>I</hi> muſt now anſwer to ſelfe-confucation.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> ſpeakes ſomething for me.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſe.</hi> l. 4. c. 27. Sect. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Qui aliquo modo in profeſſione ſua ad Eccleſiam pertinent, ſed foedus tamen Des apert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> violant, corum Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes cum aliquo diſcrimine debent Baptizari: it a ſcilicèt ut quod foedus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit, &amp; in ipfis deeſt, per aliquos quantum fieri poteſt ſuppleatur.</hi> 1. <hi>Nam diſtinctio aliqua inter puros &amp; impuros debet in ſacris omnibus obſervari, ad bonorum conſolationem; correctionem malorum, &amp; omnium adificationem.</hi> 2. <hi>Inſtituta Dei non poſſunt aliter ab omni pollutione couſervari.</hi> The Doctor <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe would have Sureties joyned, but if theſe Sureties cannot bee proved to be an appointment of God, then hee is yet ſtronger for mee.</p>
            <p>By this time <hi>I</hi> hope <hi>I</hi> have cleared my ſelfe in the Judgement of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Reader from <hi>Selfe-confutation;</hi> I knew this <hi>Church-memberſhip</hi> was the ſtrongeſt Argument that could be brought, and therefore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned it; that Church-members might challenge any Ordinance, while let alone, <hi>I</hi> could not thinke otherwiſe, but that therefore <hi>I</hi> was bound to adminiſter the Seals, as if their challenging, which comes onely by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Toleration in the Church, would make my Adminiſtration warrantable, though they are never ſo wicked, and tolerated ſinfully, this <hi>I</hi> could not believe. So that my <hi>Selfe confutation</hi> ariſeth from ſomething, you put upon mee, which <hi>I</hi> owne not; the great ſtrength then of your Booke againſt me, <hi>I</hi> hope is weakned, and all thoſe anſwers from hence, which you make great uſe of, are no anſwers.</p>
            <p>Before <hi>I</hi> paſſe to a further examination of your Anſwer, let me pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound one thing more, wherein I heartily deſire ſatisfaction from you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not cleare in the thing my ſelfe, <hi>viz. Whether all the People in England</hi> (under which we comprehend <hi>Wales</hi>) <hi>be Members of true Churches?</hi> for if it can be proved that all the Congregations in <hi>England,</hi> are not true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, then I ſhould have an Argument ſtrong enough againſt you: but ſir, I am not ſo ſatisfied to ſay they are not, nor yet ſo cleare to ſay they are; Therefore I deſire to learne.</p>
            <p>In my Booke P. 43. I ſaid <hi>I did but faintly acknowledge ſuch a thing that all are Church members:</hi> but afterward when I came to write in defence of the godly Presbyteriall Miniſters [whom I honour and reverence] againſt the Separatiſts, I ſaid I dare not undertake to prove all the Congregations in <hi>England</hi> to be true Churches: ſo that I doe not fly back, becauſe of your Booke,<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> it was done long before, ſeriouſly debating with my ſelfe, what the Separatiſts would urge againſt me, thus I phanſied they would argue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Church is a company of thoſe who are called</hi> [and this call muſt be anſwered, or elſe it is nothin <hi>To the viſible profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt, and obedience unto Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ius Divin. <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>according to the Gospell.</hi> This is the Preybyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians definition, ſay they.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52370:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But divers of the Congregations in the</hi> North <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>and other places, are not ſuch Companies, &amp;c.</hi> Ergo, <hi>they are no Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Definitio conſtat ex eſſentialibus:</hi> and definitions if true are eternally true. Now how can there be the effect where there is not the eſſentiall cauſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own grant?</p>
            <p>
               <q>I would have anſwered, if you ſpeake of a <hi>pure</hi> viſible Church, you ſay right: but there may be a <hi>true</hi> Church viſible, though divers corrupt Members, as in <hi>Corinth, Sardis,</hi> &amp;c.</q> To this I conceived they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thus, as for <hi>Corinth, Sardis,</hi> &amp;c. We doe not deny it, for there were reall Chriſtians, and viſible Chriſtians alſo, (though there were corrupt ones,) and theſe held up the eſſentiall cauſe of the Church: but in divers of theſe Pariſhes we ſhall not ſinde foure it may be ſo much as viſible Saints, if we take in knowledge, and what that definition, and Mr <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drys</hi> qualifications require for a viſible Saint.</p>
            <p>Beſides what <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Sardis</hi> had,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> was only by way of <hi>Calling</hi> as ſay the <hi>London Miniſters:</hi> but what ours are, was and is by the Sword of the Magiſtrate, King <hi>Henry</hi> the highth he left us Popiſh. King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, he takes away the Maſſe-booke, and ſends the booke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Common-prayer, though the people love the other way, yet if the King will have it ſo, it muſt be ſo. Queene <hi>Mary</hi> comes and ſhee turnes about againe, the people follow her. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſhee takes away Maſſe againe, <hi>if it were ten times in a yeare ſaith Mr.</hi> Rogers,<note place="margin">Fox Mart. vol.<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the people will turne with the state.</hi> This is the <hi>Call,</hi> and what have we now? but divers ignorant ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſent into theſe places to read a booke of <hi>Common prayer,</hi> and this is their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: this is ſtrange making of Churches, this was not ſo in the times when Churches were firſt conſtituted.</p>
            <p>Such Churches they were at their firſt conſtitution, according to Mr. <hi>Cawdric</hi> Papge 7. who doth not regard what they were before this time, ſo from firſt to laſt it is hard to ſay of divers Pariſhes that there have been ſo many viſible Saints as might make a Church.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Page you tell us. <hi>That ſome people received the Gospell after the Example of Kings, and were Baptized for company</hi> (<hi>as</hi> Simon Magus <hi>it ſeemes</hi>) but ſtay ſir, the Text ſaith, <hi>he believed</hi> (I know not in truth) and continued with <hi>Philip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his converſation was ſuch as for ought I can ſee till <hi>Peter</hi> came downe, they had good opinion of him.<note place="margin">8 Act. 13.</note> Reverend <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the Text doth not judge ſo ſlightly as you here expreſſe, and your ſelfe, Pape 17. ſpeake more clearly of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> then you doe here, and neerer the truth.</p>
            <p>Now ſir you ſay <hi>though the People thus follow onely for company</hi> [though the caſe was otherwiſe here, for the People would not have changed had they been left to their own Libertie, but the ſeare of a King or a Queen compelled them] <hi>Yet if they take upon them an outward profeſſion, that was ſufficient to give a right to themſelves, and their children for Baptiſme: and conſequently they were a true Church, though not a perfect and pure Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52370:11"/>
            <p>But ſir, you are ſpeaking of the firſt Title to Baptiſme, what a ſtrange Profeſſion doe you make here to give Title, how much different from what you have ſaid before, is required to make a Church-member?</p>
            <p>You ſay,<note place="margin">Page 7.</note> 
               <hi>it is a true Church,</hi> how will you predicate <hi>Truth</hi> of an effect, when it wants the eſſentiall cauſe? to predicate <hi>verum</hi> or <hi>vere</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> is good, but how is here the entity of a Church, when the <hi>materiall</hi> cauſe is wanting? and if the <hi>materiall</hi> be wanting, the <hi>formall</hi> is alſo, The <hi>formall</hi> cauſe, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>materiall</hi> which it doth informe, and diſtinguiſh, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſhould further have objected againſt the Separatiſts; <hi>what will you make of thoſe Pariſhes, are they Infidells?</hi> They would anſwer, let them be what they will, they are not, nor ever were (that we know, or others) fit matter for Churches; if the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will ſtand to their own Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but they would ſay againe, they are <hi>State-chriſtians</hi> made ſuch by the power of the <hi>Civill Sword,</hi> not <hi>Church-christians</hi> made by the <hi>spirituall Sword.</hi> And this ſhewes it that in their Religion, they will not go one ſtep beyond, what the <hi>State</hi> commands: and had the <hi>State</hi> let them alone, they would ſtill have held to their <hi>Popery.</hi> And talke to them of any other Church, but the place they met in, they underſtand you not.</p>
            <p>Had I ſaid, <hi>But they are Baptized,</hi> they would anſwer, if men will abuſe Baptiſme, as if a Miniſter ſhould go and Baptize <hi>Indians,</hi> muſt we needs ſay therefore they are a Church? Baptiſme doth not make a Church, for it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth a Church.</p>
            <p>The ſum is, I ſaw ſo much difficulty that I did rather avoid that, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke to prove that <hi>many</hi> Congregations were true Churches, beſides thoſe which you call Independent Churches.</p>
            <p>In this therefore I deſire ſatisfaction, and hope I ſhall ſee ſomething by this occaſion, but I am ſure it would trouble holy Miniſters to goe into ſuch places, and Adminiſter Baptiſme to the people abiding, as now they are.</p>
            <p>And now ſir, I come to examine your anſwer, and the many faults you finde with me, I ſhall take the Booke as it lies, and goe over every page, as brieſly as I can.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Page 1.</note> your queſtion, <hi>whether I meane that all theſe meete in one perſon,</hi> Ignorant, Scandalous, &amp;c. or <hi>ſingly of any of them.</hi> Sir, I was thinking of it my ſelfe, but I did ſuppoſe the Reader would underſtand me to meane <hi>ſingly,</hi> if men were <hi>groſſely ignorant,</hi> and would continue ſo wilfully, though they are intreated, and aſſiſtance offered to helpe, but will not (as is the caſe with us) ſuch deſerve Excommunication, and you affirme as much P. 17:19.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Scandalous converſations, Scoffing at godlineſſe,</hi> I ſuppoſed no queſtion would be made of it.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Submitting to Church-Diſcipline,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 2.</note> though I know ſome few <hi>Eraſtins</hi> did deny it, yet the bulke of Chriſtians would never queſtion it, being ſo plaine; but however you finde afterward that I ſpeake of ſuch as are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52370:11"/>convinced of it (which was my caſe) but becauſe I did not put it into the queſtion (though I expreſſe it afterwards) you take advantage againſt me p. 18, 19, 20.25. no leſſe then ſoure times to make it ſerve for an anſwer torne. Well Sir, I perceive your minde is not to make any favourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, though you have my minde cleared in another place, onely you lye on the catch.</p>
            <p>Come on then Sir, ſince this is your ſpirit, let us ſee whether this will give you ſuch an advantage: the queſtion is, whether <hi>Miniſters are bound to baptize Children of Parents groſlyignorant,</hi> &amp;c. Yes, ſaith Mr. <hi>C.</hi> the Parents are Church-members, and though notoriouſly ſcandalous they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to all Ordinances, while they are tolerated: tolerated ſay I, what meane you by that? you anſwer, the Church hath not proceeded to Cenſure and Excommunicate, for till excommunicated they are Church-members [yea and then alſo by your Doctrine] but then ſay I, for excommunication, I know no ſuch thing, nor any Church-diſcipline: you ſay there are godly ones not covinced of this Ordinance, and if godly ones, then not wicked ones, ſure enough they may as well renounce it: thus Diſcipline is rejected by all: ſo then <hi>non-excommunication, non-cenſuring</hi> doth not help one whit, but their groſſe ignorance, &amp;c. is ſufficient for me, for <hi>Excommunication</hi> there is no ſuch thing, ſo my arguments ſtand the ſtronger, unleſſe there be a way to help by the pro-parent and Adoption, which are your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>I ſee Sir you will plead any thing to make an anſwer, and ſeeme to ſhake hands with the <hi>Eraſtians,</hi> but if you and other Miniſters (as I perceive ſome ſuch) be ſo favourable to the opinion, then never open your mouths more for Church government: O ſay you and others, there are godly people of the opinion, well Sir, what then? put caſe Maſter <hi>Caw.</hi> is not of the opinion, but his Members are; ſuppoſe there were ſome ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Member to be excommuicated, you would doe it, and you exhort the body to conſent to you in it [to doe it, <hi>renitente plebe</hi> is a poore thin they riſe up, no ſir, wee will not conſent to you in it, for wee know no ſuch Ordinance, wee will hold Communion with him, theſe are godly perſons, now what will you doe? what brave worke we make in pleading for opinions.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>explicite Church-Covenant</hi> you ſpeake of in this page, I will let it alone till p. 5. where you revive it againe.</p>
            <p>Then your chearſe Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> ſentence and there ſinde that I doe not accord with him: If not, then I pray lee this convince you, that you have not ſpoken right, when you ſaid, <hi>I borrow my grounds from Mr.</hi> Hooker,<note place="margin">In your Epiſt. to the Reader.</note> how doe I borrow my grounds from him to whom I goe Croſſe, as you ſay I doe? if I had done ſo, Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> is a man of whom one may bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but I doe not remember what ground I borrowed, but I was glad when I ſaw ſo learned and holy a man to defend ſome things which before I conceived were right but, as to this difference here, I am ſure Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> were now alive in <hi>England</hi> he would not baptize all the children of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52370:12"/>any of the Congregalons d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England</hi> without any more adoe, I can gather ſo much out of his Booke, and therefore we doe not differ in this.</p>
            <p>Then you come to my firſt premiſe, which is, [The Infant abſtracted from the Parens,<note place="margin">Page 3.</note> gives no reaſon why it ſhould be baptized] <hi>this ſay you is otherwiſe propounded by Mr.</hi> Hooker [then its unlikely to be borrowed of him] <hi>then you tell me it is not rightly propoſed:</hi> yes Sir; very right: it is ordinary with Divines to lay a propoſition firſt further off,<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> then to come nearer; neither doe I ſee that you have one whit conſured it but yeelded it: doe you baptize any Child in your pariſh without conſidering it in relation to a Parent? do you conſider it in it ſelſe abſtracted from any other, and yet baptize it? I pray make an argument out of that Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in your Title<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, <hi>Mar,</hi> 10.14. (which I preſlime you bring for Infants baptiſme) and conſider the Infant alone as abſtracted from the Parent: you ſay preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here, the <hi>Children of</hi> England <hi>are Chriſtians borne,</hi> how? by reaſon of the houſe, ſoile, or the Parent? then its a Chriſtian child, and in relation to ſuch a one it is baptiſed. Thus you finde fault with Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> but if you will croſſe him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatr.</hi> 185.</note> or my ſelft [who am not worthy to be named in the day with him] lay downe this propoſition, <hi>viz. The Infants of</hi> England quâ ſic, <hi>conſidered as abſtracted from any where, ought to be baptiſed;</hi> if you will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this, then I confeſſe you may finde faule.</p>
            <p>For your ſecond Anſwer, when any body practiſe as you ſay there, then let ſuch a one conſider it: you might have ſpared thoſe lines, for I know none ſuch: I doe it before the child is brought.</p>
            <p>Then you come to the ſecond premiſe; [The child is baptiſed as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in relation to a parent one or: both; that is the ſumme] <hi>You ſay M.</hi> Hooker <hi>and</hi> I <hi>meane the taxt parent;</hi> and this you have conſured largely (that is your meaning) in <hi>Diatr.</hi> p. 187. of that hereafter. Only now you adds,</p>
            <p>Firſt, your ſay, <hi>thin ineffect is the ſame with the former: one the Negative, the other the Affirmative:</hi> true Sir, I know it before, onely for cleareneſſe ſuke, as we uſe to openitings firſt by ſhewing what they are not [as ſaith, love, union with Chriſts &amp;c.] then what they <hi>are,</hi> ſo I did here, and I hope no fault in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you tell me of two other wayes for children to come to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme beſides the next parent:<note place="margin">Page 5.</note> of which hereafter.</p>
            <p>Next, you ſay I take occaſion to deſine a Church. A ſociety of viſible Sains joyned togethers by way of covenant, &amp;c. Here you obſerve two things 1. <hi>That I owne no Cathelique Church but a particular Congregation, nor any Members of a Church, but of ſuch a Church; then you clime of a man being a Member onely of the Catholike Church, and by vertue of that requires Baptiſme for his child:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> For a Catholike Church, yes I owne it, neither doe I know any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding man deny it, but I doubt you forget one word, you meane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like viſible Church: but if you had ſaid ſo, yes in I owne that alſo,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52370:12"/>but whether it be <hi>one Organitall body,</hi> I ſaw ſome difficulties in that, and left in for further time to diſcover: the Congregationall men for ought I can diſcerne owne it ſo as nothing, but <hi>Nor.</hi> and <hi>Ex</hi> part you and them in the concluſion in point of Diſcipline. I know for adminlſtring the Seals in another Congregation, which that notion brings in, there ſome Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall men differ, and ſo for one Miniſter to excommunicate in another Congregation, that they will not owne (nor doe you but upon a call) they will goe along with other Officers and aſſiſt them in clearing out things, and helping them what may be, onely they will not put forth ſuch power againſt ſuch to whom they are no Officers. I trouble not theſe holy men, in that thoſe who will differ with ſuch men upon theſe points I thinke doe not well. The other part doth not concerne my queſtion, neither am I ſo cleare in it as I wiſh I were, I ſhall humbly propound my thoughts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If a man muſt firſt be a Member of a particular-viſible-Church before he can be of the Catholike-viſible-Church, then your notion will not hold, but the Antecedent is true <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Conſequent is true.</p>
            <p>Antec. I prove:</p>
            <p>If a man muſt firſt be caſt our of a particular-Church before hee can out of the Catholike, then a man muſt firſt be a Member of a Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar before he can be of the Catholike Church: but the Antecedent is trues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſequence is cleare to me on this ground.</p>
            <p>Elſe I cannot ſee how he who is caſt out of a particular Church, can be caſt out of the Catholique Church:<note place="margin">Though ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated unjuſtly, yet till caſe be heard, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Concil. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll. Can.</hi> 17.</note> if a man be firſt a Member of a particular Church, and by vertue of this comes to have communion with all other Churches, this latter depending on the former, then the reaſon is cleare; caſt him out of a particular Church you cut him off from all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with others.</p>
            <p>But if a man be firſt a Member of the Catholique Church, and his being a Member of this particular Church, depends upon that, then I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for though you have caſt him out of your particular Church which is ſecond, yet his memberſhip to the Catholique Church, which is firſt and independent upon this, ſtill remaines; and you doe in excommunication but caſt him into, that ſtate he was in before he joyned to you; ſo that ſtill he is a Member of the Catholique Church, and may demand ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces elſewhere. Other Churches deny not communion before the particular doth of which he is a Member, then they follow: hence their Act depefids on this: if depend, then not firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſeemes a little odde to me, a man is a Member of the Catholike Church onely: thence he will require <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of this Church, of another Church he will require the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> in another there he will <hi>beare,</hi> to he may go to all Churches, in the world (if he could) and demand any Ordinances, yet Member of no particular Church; ſo let this man walke as diſorderly as he will (as the latitude ſometimes you give of a Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52370:13"/>will allow a man to be bad enough) in this Towne or another Towne, he have owned no particular Church, onely the <hi>Catholike,</hi> what hath this particular Church to doe to meddle with him more then any other? wee muſt have <hi>Catholike</hi> Church-Officers to caſt him out, who are ſuch, not onely <hi>actu primo</hi> but <hi>actu ſecundo,</hi> which you ſay no Miniſter is to another that is not of his particular Congregation unleſſe he be <hi>Called</hi> to it, but to be ſure this man will never call you to it, who then can give you a Call, ſo that this man cannot come to be reformed, and yet he may goe up and downe to any Church? <hi>I am a Chriſtian,</hi> therefore give me the Ordinances, excommunicated I am not, for none can excommunicate him unleſſe all the Officers of the Churches in the world ſhould meet to caſt him out.</p>
            <p>If you ſay,<note place="margin">Which you affirm, <hi>Diatr.</hi> 194.</note> 
               <hi>Where he firſt came to be baptized, of that particular Church he is a Member, and that Officer hath power,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>No Sir, I cannot believe this doctrine, that my baptizing of another makes him member to our particular Church. I have had three of my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren baptized by Miniſters who never looked on me as member to their Church, though I dwelt in the Town, I have done the ſame for others (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to it) yet none of my members. Your ſelfe acknowledge, <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme doth not make a member of a viſible Church, Revie.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. then not of this particular viſible Church.</p>
            <p>If you ſay,<note place="margin">So you expreſs your mind. <hi>pag.</hi> 194. <hi>Diat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>But a Chriſtian muſt not doe thus, he muſt joyne to a particular Church:</hi> the queſtion is not what he <hi>muſt</hi> doe, but what he <hi>will</hi> doe: will not you baptize his child or him unleſſe he <hi>will</hi> joyne? If not, you have ſaid enough.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To be a <hi>Church-member</hi> ſeemes to be more then a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> i. e. a Chriſtian member of ſuch a Society and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>king under ſuch a policy; and that policy ſuppoſe Officers. You ſay <hi>there is no eſſentiall Homogeneall Church exiſting without Officers, mentioned in the Scripture, it is a fancy you ſaye</hi> and repeat it againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Review</hi> Maſter <hi>Hooker,</hi> pag. 75 77.</note> oppoſing Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> a Church-member then muſt be under Officers, under ſuch a policie, as in the Catholike Church, but how that can be unleſſe he be a member of ſome particular Church (which is a member of the Catholike, as you ſay) I know not: the Catholique Church hath no policy, <hi>extra eccleſias particulares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The hardeſt matter is the Apoſtles baptizing which is often abledged, this makes me doubtfull on the other ſide, onely theſe thoughts I have bad.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They had ſuch power as we have none, they could exerciſe their power any where without any <hi>call. Paul</hi> was an <hi>Actuall</hi> Officer to the <hi>Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> and ſo other Apoſtles where they came, hence they could reach them in caſe of irregular walking without a ſecond Call, but ſo much can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not we.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I doe not remember they baptized any ſingle perſons but ſuch as were members of the Jewiſh Church, which was a Goſpel-Church under cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. For others they baptized ſo many at once for ought I can ſee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52370:13"/>that might lay the foundation of a particular Church; the Jaylour <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 32. how many were in his houſe I know not, <hi>He and all his houſe believed in God.</hi> So <hi>Cornelius,</hi> there was company enough to begin a particular Church, for ought I can ſee, though how many its uncertaine: <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Puer</hi> Officers to theſe. In beginnings ſome things may be extraordinary, as were they Officers extraordinary.</p>
            <p>I eaſily ſee difficulties,<note place="margin">In N. E.</note> if one or two Indians ſhould ſeeme to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, but becauſe their language cannot joyne to an Engliſh Church, ſhould now the Miniſter delay to baptize him? but then there is this alſo, if theſe two or one ſhould prove vile and ſcandalous, what ſhall that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter doe with him? other ſcruples about this I could caſt in; but it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes not my queſtion.</p>
            <p>The next fault you finde is, <hi>That requiring an explicite covenant to ſuch a Church, I ſeeme not only to contradict my ſelfe, but alſo to unchurch moſt of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I muſt ſtay a while, having occaſion given to looke back into your <hi>Epiſtle.</hi> What doe I heare of <hi>contradictions</hi> againe? you have a ſtrange Art in finding out <hi>contradictions:</hi> but how come this about? it ſeemes I require an <hi>explicite</hi> Covenant: But Sir, are you ſure the word <hi>explicite</hi> is in the definition? nay, you are ſure tis not: Can there be no Covenant in a Church but explicite? I ſuppoſe yes, and I ſuppoſe you thinke ſo alſo, ſo doe <hi>Appollonius,</hi> we will heare him ſpeake preſently; is this fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dealing to force a word upon me when I have clearely before expreſſed my ſelſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way? I am farre enough then from contradictions, or from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching the faithfull Congregations of <hi>England</hi> though they have not an <hi>expl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Covenant: your ſelfe p. 25. mention the <hi>externall Covenant of the Church,</hi> but what you meane by it I know not.</p>
            <p>You are a paſſage in my Boiſtle which is this <q>[Some Miniſters ſcorne the notion that an explic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie Covenant is the forme of a Church viſible, and ſome profeſſours are ſo rigid for it that without it, they deny all Churches]</q> 
               <hi>of the latter ſort is Mr.</hi> Hooker, ſay you; Sir, you wrong him exceedingly, and I wonder a man of your grace ſhould doe thus when he hath ſo expreſly declared his minde to the concrary; to your knowledge the next words you mention ſhew as much, and in his Epiſtle p. 11. he ſpeaks as plaineſy. But of him anon.</p>
            <p>That paſſage ſhall cleare me from making no Churches but where there is an explicite Covenant; I ſaw in ſome Congregations where there were both viſible and reall Saints (as we may judge) when the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was to be adminiſtred, ſome profeſſours would not joyne in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for want of that (ſo farre as I could learne) ſuppoſing they were not in a right Church-way. Now this I could not approve of ſince there were ſo many Chriſtians to depart from the Ordinance upon ſuch a ground.</p>
            <p>In my owne Congregation I thus practiſe; Some of other Pariſhes have deſired to joyne with us at the Lords Supper, if we have not knowne them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52370:14"/>well, I have deſired them to bring a Teſtimony from their Miniſter, and they have done ſo: Others whom we knew well I have not deſired it, but admitted theſe to the Lords Supper, yet they were under no explicite Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but an implicite Covenant (I knew they cloſed with their Paſtors) in their Churches. If need had beene I would have baptized their children, had they brought them to me. I hope now you are convinced.</p>
            <p>Afterward you ſay againe I recall it, becauſe I ſaid, [that this explicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is <hi>almoſt</hi> eſſentiall to the government of the Church.]</p>
            <p>Why doe you not take notice of the word <hi>Almoſt,</hi> which implies there may be ſome government without it? but it will not go on ſo ſtrongly nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, but caſt what you have ſaid into a Syllogiſme, and ſee how I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call it.</p>
            <p>If expliciteneſs of covenant be requiſite to the <hi>eſſe</hi> of Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen an explicit covenant is requiſite to the <hi>eſſe formale</hi> of a Church.</p>
            <p>But the Antecedent is true: <hi>Ergo,</hi> I ſee no reaſon for the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <p>But for Church-government, try you what you can doe onely by vertue of their Chriſtianity, and implicite Covenant, I have tryed it and found it not ſufficient, but the other I have had good experience of. But for Church-convenant a few words.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſet us heare <hi>Apollonius</hi> ſpeake who is a <hi>Presbyterian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concedimus foedus aliquod tacitum ſeu virtuale eſſe inter membra unius &amp;, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem particularis Eccleſiae externae: quo obligantur ad mutua illa officia praeſtanda, quae à membris Eccleſiae viſibilis ad particularem ſuam Eccleſiasticam Communicnem exiguntur: quod nempe ſuis paſtoribus corum Curae &amp; diſciplinae ſubeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undum publicum divinum Cultum frequentare, cadem lege &amp; juriſdictione Ecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſticae gubernare velint:</hi> ex quo foedere etiam jus ſibi acquirunt, <hi>ad illa qua buic particulari Eccleſiae eju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qu: membris ſint propria, &amp; altis Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is particularibus nou Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tunt.</hi> This man ſpeakes rationally, and thoſe words are worth the obſervation, <hi>ex quo foedere jus ſibi acquirunt,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that all the right and power that Officers or particular Churches have over their members ariſe from this Covenant: and this is certaine, for ſuppoſe one be a Chriſtian, and ſuppoſe he owne Church-Diſcipline, yet how doe I in particular come to be bound to diſpenſe Baptiſme or Lords Supper to him more then any other Miniſter? or how doe I and this Church in particular more then another come to have power over another in reſpect of Diſcipline, but by his covenanting, conſenting (call it what you will) with me and this Church, and not with another? for elſe he will ſay, though I doe owne Church. Diſcipline, yet who gave you power over me more then another Officer or Church?</p>
            <p>For me to ſay you dwell in my <hi>Bariſh,</hi> is a ſilly anſwer, unleſſe it can be proved that Pariſhes were by divine inſtitution to ſuch an end: there are thoſe in my pariſh that come not to heare me, nor ever choſe me to be their Officer, nor will owne the Church in this time of reforming, but I ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52370:14"/>thinke it abſurd to tell them you dwell in this <hi>Pariſh,</hi> therefore you are bound to heare me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>One word more about Pariſhes: I would put this queſtion, it is a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in <hi>England</hi> for a Patron to preſent, of late I know where a godly Miniſter was choſen by the people, yet it being a Sequeſtration, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent dying, the gift fell into the hand of the Patron; he being an idle companion turned out the godly Miniſter, and put in another that is, &amp;c. the people with one conſent did declare againſt him, and oppoſed him at his comming, yet it ſeemes becauſe the Law of the Land will have it ſo, this man is he that hath the place; but is he therefore their Paſtour becauſe he pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chech in their Pariſh? I thinke it were ſtrange for any man to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it, and this practiſe is very common: I hope the meere pariſh doth not make him their Paſtour, nor the people his Members. This is a wofull plague to godly people, and teach the way to Separation, though it will not juſtify others where the caſe is not the ſame.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> tells us of a <hi>vinculum ſpeciale</hi> which he calls <hi>Foedus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medul. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol. <hi>cap. 32.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>ſo as no man is rightly admitted into the Church, but by confeſſion of Faith, and promiſe of Obedience.</hi> And this <hi>Apollonius</hi> ownes, <hi>pag.</hi> 13, 14.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Belgick</hi> Churches ſaw ſomething in it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol.</hi> c. 1. p. 9.</note> that it was concluded upon in ſixe Synods, that thoſe who came to the Lords Supper, ſhould promiſe expreſly to be ſubject to Diſcipline: and had the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ches of <hi>England,</hi> the godly Officers (eſpecially) made all thoſe who came into their Pariſhes, and would have either Baptiſme or Supper, to declare their choiſe of them for their Officers, and ſubjection to all Chriſts Ordinances, they might have had more ſtrength againſt the Separation: indeed they have ſtrength enough againſt moſt of them who have owned the Miniſters, and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attended, and received the Ordinances from them, of which I have ſpoken elſewhere.</p>
            <p>Further, I ſhould much deſire that thoſe who oppoſe the Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, would lay down a Church-member in his eſtentiall cauſes, then they teach cleareſt: as for profeſſion, Chriſtianity [or what you will call this is but the <hi>cauſa materialis</hi> of a Church member, for it is not Man <hi>quâ ſio</hi> (for then all) but Man <hi>quâ profeſſing, as Saint viſible,</hi> that is the <hi>materialis cauſa,</hi> this then is not the <hi>formalis cauſa,</hi> for to have the <hi>ſame thing</hi> to be <hi>Cauſa materialis &amp; formalis respectu ejuſdem effecti</hi> is ſtrange: therefore till I ſee a better I muſt ſay, that this Chriſtians conſenting or covenanting with this particular Church, and theſe Officers in it, to walke according to the Goſpell, &amp;c. is the formall cauſe of this Church-member.</p>
            <p>In ſome ſenſe we may ſay, the matter doth diſtinguiſh things, a lump of Gold, from a lump of Clay differs materially: but one Golden veſſel differs not from another, but <hi>per formam:</hi> Chriſtians as viſible Saints or Churches conſtituted of ſuch, differ materially from all other Societies of Men, but how one Church, a Golden Candleſtick differ from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but <hi>per formam,</hi> I know not, which is this that our Congregationall men ſpeak of.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:52370:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Of the reſt durſt none joyne</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) what was that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that glewed them to the Church? they were not ſcared from owning of Chriſt, or loving of the Diſciples, they might hear the Apoſtles preach, &amp;c. there was ſomething expreſſed ſure, much more now when ſo many Churches: the ſame word is uſed of the prodigall, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Covenant between. Maſter and Servant, is the glue that joynes each to other; ſo for ought I know it muſt be here.</p>
            <p>You tell me,<note place="margin">Epiſtle.</note> 
               <hi>that the relation of Chriſtians one to another, is not free but after a ſort naturall, as that of Father and Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was there ſpeaking of Church-government, how we came to have power, &amp;c. now it ſeems by you it is as naturall for any Chriſtian to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my power in particular, and this Church in particular, as for a child to be under his Fathers government, and I may naturally claim this officiall power over him, whether he will chooſe me or not, nay though he declare he will not own me for an officer, this is ſtrange Doctrine. Is his relation to me <hi>Naturall</hi> (as I am an officer) or <hi>free?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>expliciteneſſe</hi> of the Covenant, I have ſeen ſo much order and comlineſſe in Churches by reaſon of it, that if I can ever attaine it I will, and ſo would M <hi>Gawdry,</hi> had he ſeen what I have ſeeen in N. <hi>England,</hi> yet I will not null all Churches for want of an explicite Covenant. I can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between <hi>eſse</hi> and <hi>melius eſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Hudſon</hi> ſhall winde up all:<note place="margin">Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dici. Cath. <hi>pag. 19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I deny not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but mutual conſent of perſons within ſuch a Vicinity, to joyn together conſtantly in the Ordinances of God, under the Inspection of ſuch and ſuch officers, is requiſite to a particular Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now give me leave to examine a little what you have writ againſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend M. <hi>Hooker,</hi> ſince the providence of God hath joyned me with ſo holy and learned a man (O that I had his Mantle) much of his diſcourſe fals in with mine, and ſo your anſwers to him ſerve againſt me, but that part I ſhall let alone.</p>
            <p>His Queſtion is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether perſons</hi> non confederate,<note place="margin">Survey part 3. pag. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo (in our ſenſe</hi> not Members of the Church) <hi>doe entitle their children to the ſeate of Baptiſme, being one of the priviledges of the Church, their Parents</hi> (though godly) <hi>being yet unwilling to come into Church-fellowſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You make very great uſe of theſe words, <hi>that perſons non. Confederate are in his ſenſe no Members of a Church:</hi> now Sir, let me move one queſtion, Whether only perſons that are in <hi>explicite</hi> Conſederacy, are to be eſteemed in M <hi>Hookers</hi> ſenſe Members of a Church? if M. <hi>Hooker</hi> have expreſſed the contrary, as he hath moſt fully, <hi>pag.</hi> 47, 48. of his firſt part, and in <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> pag. 11. where he ſaith expreſly, <hi>The Faithfull Congregations in</hi> England <hi>are true Churches,</hi> then that cannot be M. <hi>Hokers</hi> ſenſe. In pag. 47, 48. he ſhewes how the Covenant is acted after a double manner, <hi>Explicitely,</hi> and <hi>Implicitely,</hi> and there ſhewes how it is acted in the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Then adds,</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52370:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>This Mr.</hi> R. <hi>cannot be ignorant of as our</hi> opinion <hi>and</hi> profeſſed <hi>apprehenſion: and I would intreat the Reader to obſerve once for all: that if he meet (with ſuch accuſations</hi> [ſuch an accuſer is Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi>] <hi>that we nullifie all Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our owne; that upon our grounds received there muſt be no Churches in the world, but in</hi> New-England, <hi>or ſome few</hi> (obſerve this) <hi>ſet up lately in Old: that we are rigid Separatiſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſuch bitter clamours, a wiſe meek spirit paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by them, as an unworthy and ungrounded asperſion,</hi> &amp;c. then ſhewes that <hi>Implicite</hi> and <hi>Explicite</hi> are but <hi>Adjuncts</hi> of the Covenant: and in ſome caſes an Implicite Covenant may be ſully ſufficient: could any man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpeak more clearly then Mr. <hi>Hooker?</hi> and could any man living ſpeak more perverſly then Mr. <hi>Caw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſtle to <hi>Sob. Anſw.</hi>
               </note> that Mr <hi>Hooker deny all Churches where there is not an explicite Covvenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To returne to his queſtion: Two things I deſire the Reader to obſerve in it:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By perſons <hi>non-Confederate,</hi> he doth not mean godly Parents that are not confederate <hi>explicitely,</hi> but if they be members of true Churches, walking in Church fellowſhip though there be not an <hi>explicite</hi> Covenant, but <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> doth not looke on theſe as falling under his queſtion, ſo have nothing to doe with ſuch now. This is moſt cleare by what I have alledged out of him.</p>
            <p>Hence there is not one ſyllable of the word <hi>explicite</hi> put into the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and afterwards [the ſame page] when Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſhewes why he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines to the negative, <hi>being moved thereto from the nature of the Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant:</hi> he doth not ſay <hi>explicite</hi> Church-covenant. Yet ſee how Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> interprets theſe words, that is,<note place="margin">Diatr. <hi>185.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>indeed the neceſſity of an explicite Covenant,</hi> and in page 184. he hath ſtated the queſtion thus: <hi>[Whether the Infants of Believers not in Covenant explicite with a particular viſible Church, may be baptized?]</hi> This is none of Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi>'s que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>Hence firſt, thoſe arguments which Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> hath drawne up in his <hi>Diatr.</hi> with Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> from the Infants of the godly Membe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of our Churches here in <hi>England,</hi> they all labour with the diſeaſe called, <hi>Ignoratio Elenthi,</hi> for he hath changed the queſtion, and doth not ſpeake <hi>ad idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence ſecondly, all that paines Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> ſpends to prove that Children may be baptized by vertue of <hi>Grandfather,</hi> or <hi>Adoption,</hi> [if he can make it out that they may be ſo] yet if ſuch a <hi>Grandfather</hi> or <hi>perſon who Adopts,</hi> be confederate, and walk in Church-fellowſhip (though not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely Confederated</hi>) this doth not trouble Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> queſtion: if that Grandfather, or perſon who Adopts, be not Confederate, then the queſtion falls upon them indeed, not elſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> queſtion then concernes onely ſuch godly Parents as are Members of no particular viſible Church, and being no Members but comming to joyne with a Church; now the queſtion will be, what <hi>explicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> may be required.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:52370:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing I obſerve in his queſtion is, <hi>That the godly Parents are unwilling to come into Church-followſhip:</hi> and here lyes the pinch of the queſtion. But this plainly implyes <hi>That Church fellowſhip is to be had, and this perſon is required by him to whom be offers his Child to be baptized, to joyne in Church fellowſhip:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5.13. There was a Church, and joyning to it I doubt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles would baptiſe.</note> if Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch fellowſhip be not to be had, then how ſhall his willingneſſe or unwil ingueſſe be knowne? let there be an object <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> or <hi>malum</hi> which the <hi>will</hi> ſhould chuſe or reject. Hence then if there could be no anſwer elſe given to what Mr. <hi>Ca.</hi> urgeth from the <hi>Jaylour,</hi> who was baptiſed though not confederate; this troubles not the queſtion, if there were no Church which did require him to joyne in fellowſhip; had there b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en a Church in <hi>Philippi,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> had required him to joyne in fellowſhip with the Church, and the Jaylour would not, then indeed Mr. <hi>Ca</hi> had brought ſomething againſt Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> if <hi>Paul</hi> would have bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed him.</p>
            <p>But yet Mr. <hi>Ca.</hi> will force it upon Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> that he muſt mean it of an <hi>explicite Confederacy</hi> whether he will or no,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatr.</hi> p. 200. Mr. <hi>Stone</hi> knew his mind, <hi>vid.</hi> ch. 5.</note> yea though he hath expreſly ſpoken to the contrary: but what is his ground? This.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> N. England (ſaith he) <hi>They refuſe to admit either our Members (though godly) to the Lords Supper, or their Children to Baptiſme, unleſſe they enter their expreſs Covenant:</hi> This is the ground.</p>
            <p>One paſſage I obſerve, you call the godly Ones <hi>our Members,</hi> but doe you looke on them as <hi>your Members,</hi> who are gone 3000. miles from you, never to ſee you more, where you can never have any inſpection over them, let them walke as they will? I am ſure they doe not thinke you are their Officers, nor doe call you ſo, how then they ſhould be ſtill your Members I cannot tell: let therefore Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſpeak for himſelfe, and out of him I will give you an anſwer, and ſhew you the reaſon is not as you ſay: Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> thus, <hi>The faithfull Congregations of</hi> England <hi>are true Churches; Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that come commended from ſuch Churches to ours here,</hi> ſo that it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to the judgement of the Church,<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eface, p. 11.</note> whence they come, that they are by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em approved and not ſcandalous, <hi>they ought to be received to Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us, as Members of other Churches with us in</hi> New England, <hi>in like caſe ſo commended and approved.</hi> Hence then Sir, is the plain reaſon, the people that goe from hence, doe quite depart from theſe Churches, ſo that they never come more under the Inſpection of the Officers and Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s here: they n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Letters teſtimoniall from you, to ſhew they are Members ſtill with you, and approved by you, and ſo commended, as ſaith Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> to thoſe Churches there, but thither they come free from all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (even in their owne account) and there let them walk as they will, there are no Churches have power to reach them, unleſſe they will joyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to one there, as they have disjoyned themſelves from your Churches here. But now make this tryall, let there go out of the faithfull Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of <hi>England,</hi> perſons, whoſe intent is not to disjoyne themſelves from you, onely they go as Merchants on ſome other errand, let the godly Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of ſuch Congregations, give a certificate under their hands, <hi>ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52370:16"/>that now àre comming to you in</hi> New England, <hi>are godly perſons, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our Churches, and walk in Church-fellowſhip with us, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t orderly, though we have no explicite Covenant; we deſire ſuch may for the time of their abode with you, be admitted to the Lords Supper, if a Child he borne to them, let it be bapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zed:</hi> and thoſe perſons when they come there walk according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſay try the Miniſters there, and I dare warrant you ſuch perſons ſhall not be denyed Communion though you have not an <hi>explicite</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>And here Sir they require no more of you, then they will give; for if any who are Members of their Churches ſhould come over from them hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bring no Letters of recommendation to the Churches here, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are Members with them there, and walk approvedly among them; if ſuch ſhould require the Lords Supper or Baptiſme here, if you will refuſe them [unleſſe they will ſhew or make it out, that they are Members there, and walk orderly, (onely their occaſions call them hither now for a time) or will joyne with you if they have left thoſe Churches] the Churches there will not be diſpleaſed with you: therefore the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that come from thence bring Letters of recommendation with them, ſhewing what I have ſaid before, and deſiring of Churches here their care over them while here they abide. And now you have the plaine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>But one word more: pag. 29. you ſpeak againſt thoſe who meddle with other Miniſters charges: thoſe who go to <hi>New England</hi> you call <hi>your Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> ſhould then the Miniſters of <hi>New England</hi> baptize, and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate (out of what Church I know not but yours, for of theirs they are no Members) your Members, they ſhould meddle with your charge, and doe a ſtrange act to excommunicate your Members when your ſelfe doe not, this is more then <hi>Claſſicall</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> power.</p>
            <p>But here you will charge Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> with a <hi>Contradiction:</hi> becauſe hee ſeemes to bee againſt this practiſe, <hi>that Members of one Congregation ſhould partake of the Sacraments in another Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> lived to have filed over his work againe, I do believe he would have conſidered this place again; but the other places are moſt plain. Yet ſomething may be ſaid for him.</p>
            <p>That Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> ſhould be againſt the giving of the Sacrament to a Member of another Congregation, who hath occaſion to be abſent from his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and is commended and approved by his own Church, this I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe.</p>
            <p>I will give you my reaſon. A neer friend of mine in <hi>New England</hi> living divers miles from Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> had occaſion to be in his Towne on the Sabbath: my friend being a Miniſter [I cannot tell whether at that time in Office or no to the Church, in the Towne where he lived] Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> got him to preach in the forenoone in his Church; at that time there was a Sacrament in the Church; my friend when he had done preaching (b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52370:17"/>ſad and oppreſſed in his ſpirits) went downe out of the Deske, and would not have ſtayed the Sacrament, but Mr. <hi>Hoo:</hi> ſteps after him, and claps hold on his ſhoulder, and pulled him back againe, and made him ſtay the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: my friend told me it was the beſt Sacrament that ever he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed.</p>
            <p>This practice of his clears him from Contradiction, and therefore that cannot be his meaning.</p>
            <p>This then I preſume is his true meaning: it was the practice of divers of us in <hi>N. E.</hi> at the firſt planting we did joyne our ſelves to this or that Church; afterwards when other Plantations were erected, for conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of dwelling, (the former Plantations being too full) we would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move and dwell there, retaining ſtill our memberſhip in thoſe churches to which we firſt joyned, and by vertue of it having letters of recommendation, did partake of the Sacraments in thoſe churches where we lived, and hence divers members lived many miles, twenty or ſixty from their owne churches, and from the inſpection of thoſe officers who had power to call them to account, and obſerve their Converſations, and yet would partake of the Sacraments ſixe or eight yeeres together in another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: this indeed he oppoſed, in ſo much that when I came away the Elders would not ſuffer it any longer: this is but rationall, and this I conceive is his true meaning.</p>
            <p>Here then as I ſaid is all the queſtion; whether or no if a godly man be member of no particular Church, and comes to demand baptiſm; may not I require him firſt, if you will have baptiſm, (being it is a church priviledge, and chriſtians ought to walke orderly,) then joyne to ſome particular church.</p>
            <p>If you require it of me,<note place="margin">Or ſo if there be more Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers then one.</note> then may not the officer demand, doe then you chooſe me as your officer, to whom you will ſubmit under Chriſt? doe you looke on this particular church as a true church of Chriſt, and will you walke with the members of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> according to Chriſts rule? will you ſubject to all Chriſts ordinances? I pray why may I not demand theſe? Conſider what <hi>Apollonius, Ames,</hi> Mr <hi>Hudſon</hi> have ſaid, the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will carry as much; for if this man will not owne me for his officer, if he will not joyne with the Church, if not ſubmit to Ordinances, what reaſon have I in particular to baptize his Child, or I and the church in particular to take more care of him then any other Church? if you ſay by his requiting baptiſm of me he profeſſe all this; no Sir, by no means, I have anſwered this already: and he may doe as ſome have done with me, that have required baptiſm of me, and have confeſſed to me that Diſcipline was an Ordinance of God, but to promiſe ſubjection to it, and to me with the Church that we in particular ſhould have power over them, they would not do it, and could tell me that I had no power over them without that their conſent; and they ſpeak truely, for they had not choſen me for their officer, though they are in the pariſh, and by their Chriſtianity I could claime no power over them more then another Miniſter.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52370:17"/>
            <p>So that if you will yeeld me this we ſhall at laſt prove that <hi>explicite</hi> conſent will be neceſſary at the firſt admiſſion.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir I thinke you have a full anſwer to your <hi>Diatribe,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> as to the point of Confederacy, with what I have ſaid I thinke to wipe off all your Arguments, as to that point, I doe not tun over all, becauſe my booke will ſwell into too big a volume; for the other things in the <hi>Diatrebe,</hi> they concerne me with him. Now then I, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>In p. 5. <hi>you tell me our Arguments for Infants-Baptiſme ſtand upon the notion of an Explicite Covenant.</hi> How true this is,<note place="margin">Page 5.</note> let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge.</p>
            <p>Then you tell me I have miſtaken <hi>Ameſius</hi> his argument for Infants Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Page 6.</note> [<hi>becauſe Children are capable of the grace of Baptiſme, for all are Patients,</hi> &amp;c.] this is brought you ſay to anſwer the objection of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> what you tell me of thoſe is no newes: but I pray ſee if Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> be anſwering an objection; hee makes is his fifth argument: ſee alſo Mr <hi>Marſhall</hi> his Sermon upon Infants Baptiſme. p. 41.43. I know it ſerves againſt an objection, and yet conſider the child with the parent, it may ſerve for a ground alſo for Baptizing.</p>
            <p>Then you tell me I ſpeake not properly, becauſe I put a <hi>Morality in that Command to Abraham</hi> &amp;c.] Sir you may well know by the next words I did but borrow the word from the morality of the ſecond commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I had uſed for illuſtration: and is there onely <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alogy</hi> in it, when we ſee the Command is not repealed, but rather confirmed in the New Teſtament?<note place="margin">Acts 2.38, 39.</note> but I perceive your ſcope is to ſpye out what faults you can, though they do not concerne the queſtion, and ſometimes when you can finde none, yet you will make ſome.</p>
            <p>Then you bring me to the queſtion about predeceſſors,<note place="margin">Page 7.</note> which you have largely diſcuſſed in the <hi>Diatrebe,</hi> you ſay, for that <hi>promiſe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandement you ſay you would not plead it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir then you doe not help my adverſaries at home, who have pleaded onely that promiſe, and therefore I onely mentioned that, not having ſeene your booke.</p>
            <p>Before I come to ſee what you have ſaid, let me ſpeake one word, as to the queſtion, <hi>whether if a godly grand-father being of the Church, and being Orthodoxe</hi> [you put it in thus twice in one page, godly, living, Orthodoxe] <hi>ſhould bring a grand-child to me, to baptize it by vertue of him taking it to himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatr.</hi> 187. and ſo in this p. 7. godly.</note> 
               <hi>as his own, and cugaging for the Education of it, whether now</hi> I ſhould refuſe it? truely I cannot tell; it is a hard queſtion, and becauſe I ſee ſo many holy learned men, and ſome alſo Congregationall men are of that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I am the more ſhaken, thinking God will reveale more to them then to ſuch a wretch as I am, but I am not reſolved what I ſhould doe, if I were put upon the practiſe.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe I yeeld this, yet you trouble me not at all but ſave my queſtion, for if I baptize it not as it is the <hi>immediate Seed</hi> of theſe Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous parents, but the <hi>mediate ſeed</hi> of a godly grand father or grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52370:18"/>who take it as theirs and engage for Education, then I doe not Baptize the children of ſuch as the queſtion mentions by vertue of them. This will ſerve to take off many of your Anſwers.</p>
            <p>But then I come againe, What ſhall I doe with the Infants of ſuch whoſe parents are ſuch as the Q. men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions, and ſo are, and were their <hi>pro-parents?</hi> I have divers ſuch, of whom I have enquired.</p>
            <p>Thus then I could eaſily depart from this, but for diſcourſe ſake, to beat it out more clearely, I will try what you have ſaid.</p>
            <p>The text you give me is <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. and in this p. and p. 11. you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of me an <hi>expeſſe Scripture</hi> that ſhews, <hi>the promiſe reach but to the next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</hi> What meane you by this? do you look on me as an <hi>Anabaptiſt?</hi> when I diſpute againſt them I take their owne principles, but doe you therfore require it of me? I doubt you have not given <hi>expreſſe Scriptures</hi> for all you have ſaid in your books. Nay Sir, (which is ſtrange) if you will prove the Grandfather might circumciſe the Grandchild, if the immediate parent had loſt his right [which come neereſt to our Q.] you muſt draw it out by <hi>conſequence:</hi> I pray call for no more then you give.</p>
            <p>Becauſe you ſpeak ſo of your <hi>full and large diſcuſſing of</hi> this queſtion in your <hi>Diatr.</hi> I made account you had beſtowed much paines upon the text to prove it out, and cleare the text, but I ſee you onely propound the text, and no more. It is worth the paines ſometimes to cleare out a text, which you have not done; that which lookes moſt likely is, that you ſay, <hi>Jacob had power to diſpoſe of Joſephs Children;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diatr. <hi>188.</hi> The iſſue which thou begetteſt after them ſhall be thine.</note> you might have ſet downe a Text: if you meane 48. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. the 6. v. will help to an anſwer, * and as for the 5. v. if you pleaſe to peruſe famous <hi>Rivet</hi> on the Text, who clearely opens it; I cannot ſee how any thing can be drawne from thence to your purpoſe, to prove it by any thing elſe you have ſaid, I can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>But to the Text: <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant betweene me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee in their generations for an everlaſting? Covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Its true, God made his Covenant not onely with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but his ſeed after him. His <hi>Seed,</hi> either 1. Such as were <hi>Carnally</hi> and <hi>Spiritually.</hi> So <hi>Jacob, David,</hi> &amp;c. who were really within the Covenant of grace.</item>
               <item>2. Or his Seed onely <hi>Carnally.</hi> So thoſe ten Tribes when revolted, and the Jewes when went whoring after Gods, not cleaving to the God of <hi>Abraham:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Who onely <hi>Spiritually</hi> not <hi>Garnally:</hi> So the believing <hi>Proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lites</hi> then, and believing <hi>Gentiles:</hi> which I conceive may be ſub-divided, into his Seed <hi>really</hi> ſo, or <hi>viſibly</hi> ſo, that in judgement of charity appeare ſo, but not truly ſo. So ſome of the Jewes alſo, as well as Gentiles.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith <hi>Hee will be a God to them,</hi> thoſe who were really and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually <hi>Abrahams Seed,</hi> had him for their God indeed: for others he was a God ſo to them as he owned them only of all nations to be his Church, giving to them his Statutes and Ordinances; they alſo <hi>His holy People,</hi> i. e. ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from other people.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52370:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="3">3. It is true, God did hold this Governant with them, he did not caſt off his Seede in the 6. or 10. generation, and take in another Seed to make his Church of, ſo long as that Policie was to endure.</p>
            <p n="4">4. However the Covenant for the ſubſtance was given to <hi>Adam,</hi> yet I conceive (under favour) it was not drawne <hi>formally</hi> into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant before now: (<hi>Noahs</hi> Covenant was a Covenant with the Creature as well as with Man.) Hence God appoints a Signe and Seale of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Covenants uſe to be fealed, not bare promiſes. This Seale is to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to <hi>Abrahams ſeed</hi> who were taken into Covenant.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion is, whether this Seale of the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> was to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to the ſeed of <hi>Abraham as ſuch,</hi> i. e. onely <hi>Carnally</hi> ſo, though they had changed their <hi>God,</hi> who was <hi>Abrahams</hi> God, and worſhipped ſuch Gods as <hi>Abraham</hi> abhorred: <hi>though they had plainely rejected the Covenant,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. from 8. to 18. v. <hi>though they were worſe then the Heathen;</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.9.11. ſo that nothing of the Covenant appeared in them, or was to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to ſuch (as viſible at leaſt) did walke as <hi>Abraham</hi> their Father did? If that be true which <hi>Maimony</hi> quoted by <hi>Ainſw.</hi> ſay it ſhould ſeem ſo. <hi>It is a generall rule, that he onely is</hi> Abrahams <hi>Seed, that reteineth his Law, and his Right way: and theſe are they that ought to be Circumciſed:</hi> if none elſe, then they did ill in Circumciſing abundance; but for ought I can learn out of the chapter, <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> though onely his ſeed according to the fleſh were to be circumciſed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Out of this I cannot ſee, but that any Child whoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father was of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, might as well be circumciſed, by vertue of a Predeceſſour who was <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, though he were dead ſix hundred years before, yea by vertue of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelfe (and that is moſt likely) as well as by vertue of a Grandfather.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It ſeemes a vaine thing to talke of a Grandfather giving right to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,<note place="margin">Sir I pray prove this that ever any did ſo. It was my 9th Argument, p. 12.</note> in caſe the immediate parent had forfeited his right (as our que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion would intimate) for if we conſider who were to adminiſter this Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and the immediate parent being of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, it ſhould ſeem there is no room for ſuch a thought.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who did adminiſter it were their <hi>Parents, Magiſtrates,</hi> or <hi>Maſters,</hi> (if Servants) yea <hi>themſelves</hi> ſay <hi>Maimony,</hi> when wax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n great,<note place="margin">Ainſw. <hi>Gen. 17.12.</hi> Buxto. Synag. Jud. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> if the thing were hid from the Judges, yea learned <hi>Rivet</hi> agrees with <hi>Abulen.</hi> who ſaid <hi>women</hi> as well as <hi>men;</hi> ſo ſay others whom I could quote, there was none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned of God to the work; and ſtill among the Jewes, he that can doe it moſt neatly he adminiſters it, whom they call <hi>Mohel;</hi> and he practiſes firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the children of poorer ſort of Jewes, then others.</p>
            <p>This ſpeaks plainly to me that it is vain to talk who gave right there, it appears plain enough.</p>
            <p>But come to us: <hi>Believers onely are Abrahams ſeeds</hi> the fleſh hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe here, there muſt be fleſh as a <hi>ſuſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um</hi> that's true, or elſe there can be no Believer, but not <hi>ſuch</hi> fleſh that comes from <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52370:19"/>Believing Gentiles, ſuch as viſible, walk as <hi>Abraham</hi> did; theſe are eſteemed his ſeed, and with theſe God makes his Covenant, theſe have the Seale ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, and their Children, God is a God to them alſo, takes them into his viſible Church, and appoints the Seale for them: but if theſe Children grow up and make it plainely appeare (that they reject the Covenant of their Fathers, and they prove contumacious, theſe ceaſe to be <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, the <hi>fleſh</hi> here will not help them: whilſt Infants they were eſteemed his, but now they declare the contrary; if then they declare open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are not his ſeed, how can they give title to the Seale of the Covenant which they have rejected?</p>
            <p>Had this Covenant (the Seale I meane) beene to be adminiſtred to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed only, ſo that if any of his carnall ſeed had manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted a rejection of the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> then they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited their right; had it beene committed to the Prieſts or Levites to adminiſter with a care that it were not abuſed; and could it be made cleare that the immediate parent might forfeit his right, and then the Grandfather gave the Title; then there were good arguing from hence; but thoſe things are yet to prove. Doth God ſay to any believing Gentile, I <hi>will bee the God of thee and thy ſeede, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Generations, though thy ſeede caſt me off?</hi> But I will come to argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the Grandfather by vertue of this promiſe can give the Title to Baptiſme, then the Children of <hi>Carpocrates, Marcion, Valentinus</hi> [let us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe mens parents to be godly and Church Members, and theſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to have Children] ought to be baptiſed.</p>
            <p>But the Conſequent is falſe. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Antecedent is falſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you ſay, that if their Grandfathers were living, and would take thoſe Children and educate them, its true they might.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray Sir why doe you tye up the Text to <hi>living</hi> Grandfathers, there is nothing like it in the Text, let the Grandfathers be living or dead, thats nothing in the Text: if they were <hi>ungodly</hi> or <hi>Hereticall,</hi> there is nothing, they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed according to the fleſh.</p>
            <p>There is nothing neither of a Grandfather taking the Grandchild to himſelfe, ſtill they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed; neither can I diſcerne how you can draw it out by neceſſary conſequence.</p>
            <p>If you ſay they are <hi>Apostates</hi> and ſo have no right: Sir the Text ſpeakes not of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, if they doe not Apoſtatize, you know they did ſo, and yet were circumciſed; and that by vertue of a grand-father is not proved. Such a Chriſt as theſe Hereticks phanſied they did owne: ſo for <hi>Arrians, Photinians,</hi> they will owne a Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the Baptizing of Hereticks children,<note place="margin">To. <hi>494.</hi> loc. com. To. <hi>4.648.</hi>
               </note> you have <hi>Walaeus</hi> againſt you, and <hi>Gerhard,</hi> the clauſe they put in, <hi>if the Hereticks ſay they will bring up their children in their Hereſie</hi> is but needleſſe, as if <hi>Hereticks</hi> would not doe ſo; what they ſay for this I can turne as well againſt ſcandalous living; but I ſhall not trouble my ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52370:19"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>You ſay this promiſe [I will be the God of thee and thy Seed]</hi> reached <hi>not onely to the next Children, but their poſterity in a ſecond or third generation:</hi> then you make an &amp;c. that is true as I have ſaid before, and it troubles not me: but now under the Goſpel to how many generations will this extend, that the Grandfather ſhall give title to Baptiſme? you name the <hi>third</hi> and then adde, &amp;c. How many doe you include in <hi>&amp; coetera:</hi> thus you have ſpoken in another place, and there another &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diatr.</hi> p. 188.212.</note> It is indeed uſuall to put an &amp;c. when mens mindes are clearly knowne, and there is no matter of conſequence attended upon it, ſo ſpare our writing, and the Printer; but if any matter of conſequence depends, then it is very poore to put in <hi>&amp; coetera,</hi> you know &amp;c. in the Biſhops Oath was an untoward thing, and here it is a troubleſome thing; if to the <hi>third,</hi> why not to the 103 genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>&amp; coetera</hi> will go further. But ſay you p. 11. <hi>this is their common Objection,</hi> [his head is very ſhallow that ſhould not reach <hi>but you have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered it elſewhere:</hi> Come on then Sir, ſince you ſay you have <hi>fully</hi> anſwered it, I will turne to your <hi>Diatribae,</hi> and there looke for it, ſuppoſing that a man of your parts who doth ſlight ſo extreamly other mens argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, calling them <hi>very weake,</hi> &amp;c. when you ſay you anſwer <hi>fully,</hi> you have done ſo indeed; in p. 212. I ſee you have it there to anſwer. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you ſinde it a troubleſome objection, and there recite the opinions of ſome men, whom I honour as much as your ſelfe, if there were nothing but an opinion of a man to be deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: you ſumme up their opinions, and it amounts to this; <hi>It ſcomes that the Children of Chriſtians knowne or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to be ſuch, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her living or dead, may be baptiſed.</hi> then you give us an alluſion from thoſe who could not prove their Genealogy. <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.62: Whether you will ſtand to this as your anſwer I know not: but then you adde, <hi>But all the Children of knowne Believers,</hi> Chriſtians, Orthodox and yet living, <hi>whether next or remoter may ſeeme to challenge a right to Baptiſme:</hi> this is the full anſwer; but twice you uſe the word <hi>ſeeme,</hi> which ſhewes you ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther propound your opinion modeſtly, but I pray Sir doe not ſay this is ſo <hi>fully anſwered,</hi> it is no anſwer at all, (it is your opinion indeed) for by all the diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe I have met with as yet in that book, you have not proved that <hi>living</hi> Grandfathers may give a title, onely you propound a text, which will prove the <hi>dead</hi> as well as the <hi>living</hi> may give a title if a Grandfather at all may: if you meane no more then the living Grandfather, your <hi>&amp; caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> will ſoone be run out.</p>
            <p>In p. 8. you meet with an argument of mine which is this,<note place="margin">Page 8.</note> 
               <q>[If the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of the immediate parent cut him off; from the Lords Supper; though his parent be godly, why doth not the ſame wickedneſſe cut him off from giving right to his childs Baptiſme? if the parent cannot claime one Seale of the Covenant for himſelfe, appearing plainely not to have the condition of it, muſt not the child ſuffer who depends upon him for its title?</q> The parent ſuffers, therefore the child muſt needes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay no, not for Temporall puniſhment</hi> [Gehezi, Achan, Corah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52370:20"/>children did] <hi>nor ſpirituall.</hi> To this I anſwered [they cannot be abſtracted from their parents in this, and therefore may: as the child comes to have its right by a parent, ſo the child may loſe by a parent: it doth not loſe ſalvation nor regeneration by it.</p>
            <p>You anſwer 4. waies: 1. <hi>From the Jewes;</hi> which doth not availe with me, there was ſomething peculiar to them in adminiſtration of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as is cleare before, and ſhall be made cleare hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Your ſecond is the diſtinguiſhing betweene a perſons generall ſtate and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall wickedneſse; his ſtate is a chriſtian, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer; if you meane by <hi>perſonall wickedneſse,</hi> ſome particular falls (as you bring in <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſtrangely afterward) I think ſo indeed; but if you meane a continued ſetled courſe in wickedneſſe, wilfull ignorance then <hi>I</hi> ſay; ſuch a perſon hath loſt his firſt right to his owne or his childs baptiſme [you may call him a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but let his <hi>Christianity</hi> be ſuch as you have ſaid may qualifie him for a Church-Member, or elſe it is not worth a ruſh.] Such a one I looke at as one that ought to be excommunicated, for he deſerves it, (we muſt prove that perſons ought to be excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before they are.) Now ſince he ought, the queſtion is, why he is not? [if he be, the child ſuffers for his <hi>ſtate</hi> being a non-Member] in <hi>foro Dei</hi> he is, and ought to be in <hi>foro Eccleſiaſtico:</hi> if the caſe ſtand ſo as through the multitude of ſuch, it cannot conveniently be ſo, Then yet let the Miniſters go as farre as they can. I pray Sir let this ſatisfie to your anſwers which you give about Excommunication; for you would gather from me, <hi>that till Excommunication, Miniſters ought to baptiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far <hi>I</hi> yeild it, till Excommunication, or that which doth deſerve Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, ſo that the perſons ought to be excommunicated, though from ſome other externall impediments (as <hi>multitude,</hi> &amp;c.) they cannot be excommunicated; yet then a <hi>ſeparation</hi> from ſuch, or <hi>non-communion</hi> may help.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You ſay, <hi>you have largely confuted this notion of the immediate parent:</hi> I think not ſo.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You ſay, <hi>I have deſtroyed it my ſelfe:</hi> the right he hath is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Churches toleration, let the Officers looke to that: the firſt and maine right hee hath none, and none at all according to your doctrine.</p>
            <p>For p. 9. the diſtinction of the <hi>Phyſical</hi> and <hi>Moral</hi> right in <hi>Diatr.</hi> 188. if you had ſtrongly proved the Moral right of the Grandfather would clearely have taken off that wrong meant. Sir I will receive an anſwer when I ſee I am anſwered. But that there ſhould be as lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le right of the Mother over the Childe when compared with her Husband, as is of the Grandfather compared with the Father (which you would ſeeme to intimate) is ſtrange, I am ſure the Mother communicates as much and more to the being of the Childe, then the Father doth.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Aquina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he may enjoy his opinion, yet I think <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mier</hi> (of whom
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52370:20"/>anon) is not full for him. For <hi>my needleſſe exception,</hi> you mention, it is well if nothing needleſſe have come from you.</p>
            <p>Then you tell me I renew my plea,<note place="margin">Page 10.</note> which is this <q>[who ſhall educate this child? the Ignorant perſon cannot, the Scandalous teach it how to breake the Covenant, Predeceſſors are dead, &amp;c.]</q> Here firſt <hi>you tell me of a Law of the Land, which bath taken care for the education of Papiſts Children, and Orphans, providing Schooles and Hoſpitalls.</hi> Hence firſt I gather, you doe not care whether the Grandfather be living or dead, which in another place you expreſſe otherwiſe; here the immediate groſly ignorant and ſcandalous perſons give title: but for what you ſay, I pray pardon my ignorance of the Lawes that have been ſo many yeares out of <hi>England;</hi> I did not know the State had made ſuch a Law, <hi>That if an Ignorant or Scandalous Parent have a child baptiſed, then thoſe who are knowing and godly men (at leaſt ſober men, converſation comely) ſhould take the child, and bring it up, and inſtruct it in the Covenant of grace,</hi> which muſt be the anſwer or nothing; this were wofull trouble, if good People or viſible Saints ſhould be thus charged with all the children of perſons who are as the queſtion mentions: As for the other part, you ſay, <hi>The Church ſhould take care, as in caſe both the Parents dye whileſt they are little Children:</hi> and then you give a nip to the <hi>Congregationall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:</hi> you ſay right for the Churches care, but how ſhall we doe whilſt theſe parents live and keepe them at home, and teach them to breake Covenant, and though they are intreated to ſend their children to catechiſing, yet will not, as I have too bad experience? For the children of Church members, the parents dying whilſt they are young, I wiſh I could ſee as good examples of your parochiall Cnogregations taking care for the Chriſtian education of ſuch, as I could give you in the Congregationall Churches in <hi>New England,</hi> but then the title was not queſtioned, there was that eaſe, and wee did not know but thoſe godly parents might live to educate them.</p>
            <p>Then p. 11. you turne an argument upon me from my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Page 11.</note> 
               <hi>[becauſe I could plead a promiſe by vertue of may Father, ſo may the Grandchild by vertue of a godly Grandfather, and ſo bid me change Parent into Progenitors.]</hi> Sir I am glad I could give you ſo good an argument, and I could beteame to let it alone, for it will not hurt my queſtion, as I ſaid before. Onely a word, you bid me change <hi>Parent</hi> into <hi>Progenitors;</hi> ſo I will, let it be the great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of the childs great Grandfather, and one that is fourty generations before him, for your <hi>&amp; coetera</hi> will give me leave, (I know not how to ſet bounds to <hi>&amp; coetera</hi>) yet I may goe ſo farre for a title, and the text you bring doth not limit me.</p>
            <p>You grant an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> loſeth his owne baptiſme, p. 12.<note place="margin">Yet you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how a parents Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off his child. <hi>Diatr.</hi> p. 190.</note> ſo his right is cut off; ſuppoſe the <hi>pro-parents</hi> be dead here is <hi>interciſio Chriſtianiſmi</hi> as you quoted <hi>Calvin</hi> before, then I know not how this Apoſtates child can be Baptized, by any parentall right: yet if this child ſhould come to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and there ſhould be movings on the heart of it, and it ſhould plead the Covenant of a Grandfather [I ſhould not queſtion to baptiſe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to parents if it came to that.] Yet Sir, this will ſhew there is a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52370:21"/>great difference betweene the pro-parents right [if it can clearely be proved at all,] giving a title to baptiſme, and the immediate parents, for that may be cut off by the immediate parent juſtly, but the immediate parents title cannot be cut off.</p>
            <p>Now we are come to the laſt Argument.<note place="margin">Page 12, 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If by vertue of the Grandfather, then the child of one Apoſtatiz'd or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated perſon may be baptiſed: but not <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For an Apoſtate <hi>you tell me of the kindred taking care of it, or ſuſceptores:</hi> this notion will come in afterwards.</p>
            <p>For excommunicated perſons there you beſtow paines, and I perceive you care not ſo much for a <hi>pro-parent</hi> here, but by vertue of the immediate parent himſelfe though excommunicated.</p>
            <p>For my owne part I ſhould not here yeeld to a <hi>pro-parent,</hi> neither doe I ſee our <hi>New England</hi> Divines (that could beteame a Grandchild under the Grandfathers tuition to be baptized by vertue of him) will allow, it if the immediate parents be excommunicated, for this hinders the working of the Ordinance; it is of greater force to worke when a man ſhall ſee not onely himſelfe cut off, but even his very children alſo, this hath beene a means to awaken ſome in <hi>N. England,</hi> who were not excommunicated, but onely not admitted, to ſee their poſterity alſo ſuffer for their ſakes, it hath ſo wrought as to make ſome truly godly (ſo farre as we may judge) and others it hath brought into externall order in converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But ſince you have here maintained it by vertue of the immediate parent excommunicated, I ſhall deſire to conſider it.</p>
            <p>It is granted there is a difference betweene an excommunicated perſon and a Heathen. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. He may ſtill hold his profeſſion:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revie.</hi> M. <hi>Hoo.</hi> 119.</note> 
               <hi>[but as you ſay, it is violated by his ſcandall, and it must be renewed before he can be received againe.]</hi> Though he holds his profeſſion ſtill, yet that now violated is not ſufficient to give him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a title to Baptiſme if he were not now baptiſed, much leſſe the child who depends wholly on his title.</p>
            <p>If his profeſſion be ſufficient to give his child by vertue of him a title to one Seale of the Covenant, why the ſame profeſſion ſhould not be ſufficient to give himſelfe a title to the other Seale of the Covenant, [one faith being the condition of it, and you ſay he hath that,] I can ſee no reaſon.</p>
            <p>That profeſſion which is not ſufficient to make a man a Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, is not ſufficient to give title to a Church-priviledge, conſequently not to baptiſme.</p>
            <p>But the profeſſion of a perſon excommunicated is not ſufficient, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo</hi> the Minor is cleare: <hi>his profeſſion is vioalated, and muſt be renewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can be received,</hi> ſay you. Then tis not ſufficient.</p>
            <p>This is further cleare, for if it be ſufficient to make him a Church-member when caſt out, why was it not ſufficient to keepe him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52370:21"/>within whilſt bee was within? ſo he ſhould not have needed to bee caſt out.</p>
            <p>This then is cleare, that there is great difference betweene the profeſſion of a perſon who was never admitted, and another who is caſt out: the firſt may have leſſe knowledge by farre, weaker gifts and poſſibly more infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which may yet be ſuch, as a Church may admit, when the other who hath violated his profeſſion, may not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is under cure, but his cure is <hi>non-memberſhip,</hi> a member cut off from the body: a Heathen is not under cure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When he hath renewed his profeſſion by repentance, and ſo the Church received him againe, he is not re-baptiſed: but this doth not prove that therefore whilſt he is <hi>extra Eccleſiam,</hi> that he can give title to a priviledge of the Church: it is not his being baptiſed that is the ground of his childs baptiſme whilſt he is in the Church, therefore that cannot give the title when he is out of the Church.</p>
            <p>But Heathens muſt be baptiſed when they are admitted: the other is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived again, not therefore baptiſed. That his baptiſme is not the ground of his childs baptiſme, I ſhall prove afterward.</p>
            <p>But I will come to Argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If a child may be baptiſe by vertue of an excommunicated parent, then that parent is not excommunicated; and this is to make a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But the parent is excommunicated. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To baptiſe is to give Communion, <hi>baptiſed into one body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13.</note> then there is Communion given with the body, by an excommu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icated perſon: is not this a contradiction? Communion is moſt properly ſeene in Baptiſme and Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is excommunication,</hi> ſaith M. Rutherf. <hi>but to deny all Communion with thoſe who were once in the Church?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peac:</hi> plea 222</note> but all Communion is not here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed.</p>
            <p>You will object, as you anſwer, pag. 13. <hi>All Communion with himſelf, but not with the child, for that is borne a Chriſtian, and ſo bath right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hath the child right to Communion any other way with the Church then by the paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? is it not he that brings him in as a branch of himſelf? is it not a Chriſtian borne by vertue of the parents Chriſtianity? but his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Chriſtianity can give himſelfe no title to Church-priviledges, as I ſaid before of <hi>profeſſion,</hi> which is all one. Doth the child plead a title diſtinct from the parent? if ſo, then your anſwer you give were ſomething, but I know of no title it hath but the parents, who expreſſes his own title for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his ſeed. Now it is ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y rationall, that if the child have Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion given onely by vertue of the parents Communion, [for before the parent was admitted a Church-member the child could have none] then the parent having forf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ited Communion for himſelfe, muſt needs forfeit it for his depending child alſo.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith of Excommunication, <hi>Apol</hi> c. 39. and l. 2. <hi>ad uxorem</hi> you know.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:52370:22"/>
            <p>If <hi>Claſſian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> his wiſe were a Church-member though her husband were caſt out,<note place="margin">Aug <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> we doe not approve his practice who would not baptize his child by vertue of her; but it ſeems they apprehended that there was ſome equitie if both were caſt out. No wonder though <hi>Auguſtine</hi> were again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it upon his principle.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If excommunication be the caſting out of a member of a Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> and conſequently rendring him a non-member, then an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated perſon cannot give title to his childs Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>But excommunication is caſting a man out &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The conſequence is cleare, how can one who is a non-member of a Church give title to a Church-priviledge?</p>
            <p>Excommunication renders him a non-member, cutting him off from Communion, and admitting him to no other Ordinances then a non-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is.</p>
            <p>The phraſe, <hi>caſt out,</hi> ſhewes he is no Member.</p>
            <p>So the phraſe of <hi>cutting off,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aar. rod.</hi> l. 1. c. 5.</note> which learned <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> hath excellently open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be meant of Excommunication, and there brings in <hi>Buxtorf.</hi> and <hi>Godwin,</hi> who report out of the <hi>Rabbius,</hi> that their children were not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. This you ſay, pag. 14. <hi>is not Orthodox, and it was a corrupt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the latter Jews having no ground for it in the Scripture:</hi> you ſay elſewhere, I thinke in the <hi>Diatr.</hi> that the Scripture doth not ſpeak <hi>for</hi> nor <hi>againſt</hi> it, ſo far as) ou can ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; but then Sir what ever I make of it, it concerns you to prove it to be a corrupt invention, though I could yeild it from what I obſerved before of their Circumciſion, and yet not hurt my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But you anſwer to this Argument, p. 13. <hi>That he is a member ſtill, though much diſeaſed;</hi> he was much diſeaſed before, whilſt under Church ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, ſuſpenſions, and becauſe thoſe Medicines would not cure him he was cut off; <hi>a member under cure,</hi> ſay you, his cure is <hi>non mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is pretty, a man ſhall be <hi>cut off the body,</hi> and yet be <hi>a member of the body;</hi> a man ſhall be <hi>caſt out of the Church,</hi> and yet ſhall'be <hi>within the Church;</hi> a man ſhall be <hi>no member of a Church,</hi> as ſay you p. 24. and p. 14. and yet be <hi>a member of a Church;</hi> how you who are ſo Eagle eyed to ſpie out contradictions in other men will now cleare your ſelfe, I cannot tell. <hi>Member, no Member,</hi> are <hi>contradicentia</hi> I thinke, and to find a <hi>medium in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicentibus</hi> is new Logick to me, I though <hi>ens &amp; non ens</hi> had admitted none.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Excommunication is the putting of a man out of the viſible King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, into the Kingdome of Satan. So the beſt Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors I meet with,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> Maſter <hi>Cartwright,</hi> &amp;c. expounds <hi>that delivering up to Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence I ague, To adminiſter the Seale of the Covenant to a child by vertue of one who is even <hi>Eccleſiaſticè</hi> in the Church repute under the Kingdome of Satan, is very unwarrantable.</p>
            <p>To make Chriſt a <hi>Politicall head</hi> to one under Satans Kingdome, ſeemes very ſtrange.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:52370:22"/>
            <p n="4">4. Excommunication is the rendering of a man <hi>as a Heathen to the Church,</hi> Mat. 18. we doe not differ here, but agree that Excommunication is meant here what ever the <hi>Eraſtians</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Here let me have leave to put in a word. The <hi>Eraſtians</hi> expound this of civill injuries, or perſonall civill treſpaſſes onely, and will prove it by comparing of <hi>Luke</hi> 17.3, 4. with this; his Argument being, <hi>Becauſe it is ſuch a trespaſſe as a brother may forgive:</hi> Mr. <hi>Gillespy</hi> beſtowes paines here, and to good purpoſe; but let it be ſuppoſed the Texts run parallel, which M <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> thinks not. 1. That <hi>Luke</hi> 17. ſaith, that a brother may forgive ſuch a treſpaſſe, as it were better a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>angedi about his neck who offers it. But 2, we finde in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 27.10. that <hi>Paul forgave,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Corinth forgave,</hi> what, a treſpaſs done againſt them? No ſure, the inceſtuous perſons act was no evill treſpaſſe againſt <hi>Paul</hi> nor the <hi>Church,</hi> yet they <hi>forgive.</hi> If then they can <hi>forgive,</hi> why may not a private brother alſo <hi>forgive?</hi> Thus it is ſuppoſed, that the ſcandall which is here given, &amp; for which the private brother dealeth with the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour privately, is but a private ſcandall, (for if it be publique, this way of dealing ceaſeth) if then this private brother dealing with the offendour finds the man to acknowledge his ſin, and repent, why may not he be ſaid to <hi>forgive</hi> him alſo? [as in caſe it had been a publike fact and caſt out, upon his repentance the Church <hi>forgive</hi>] ſo that now he embraceth him in his heart againe, proceedes not to call any other to deale with him, nor to tell it to the Church, but the ſcandall is buried, forgiven, forgotten, <hi>Eccleſiaſticè:</hi> I know no abſurdity in this, and ſo the forgiveneſs doth not prove it to be a civill treſpaſſe onely.</note> ſay.</p>
            <p>Had Chriſt ſaid, <hi>let him be a Heathen</hi> (with reverence be it ſpoken) it ſhould ſeeme not to have beene ſo proper a ſpeech, for he may not be <hi>a Heathen,</hi> for he may hold his profeſſion though caſt out, and ſo is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>a Heathen,</hi> but as <hi>a Heathen</hi> he is to the Church; now what that is Mr. <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> tells us (and not he alone, but others) plainely:<note place="margin">Aaro. rod <hi>382.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he is to be uſed no better then an Heathen or prophane Publican, and is not to be admitted to any Ordinance, except ſuch as Heathens and prophane Publicans were admitted to.</hi> But were they admitted to the Circumciſion of their children?<note place="margin">Page 392.</note> againe he opens it, <hi>let him be eſteemed as one that hath no part in the Communion of Saints, in Church-memberſhip</hi> (obſerve that, no Member then) <hi>in the holy things, in the Covenants, of promiſe, more then a heathen man.</hi> How then ſuch a one ſhould give title to the ſcale of the Covenant I cannot tell.</p>
            <p>For the text you bring in <hi>Diatr.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14, 15.<note place="margin">Page 218. <hi>Rhem. Teſt.</hi>
               </note> If you pleaſe to view Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> on the text, you will finde he gives reaſons why that text moſt properly is meant of <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> not <hi>Excommunication;</hi> ſo in his <hi>Harmony</hi> upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. he expounds this of <hi>Suspenſion: the text ſaith you are to account him a Brother, but the excommunicated perſon (till repentance) is no otherwaies to be eſteemed then as a Heathen;</hi> ſaith he, true, that which is cauſe of Suſpenſion is cauſe of Excommunication, if not repented of. But I believe this text is the cleareſt you can have for <hi>Suſpenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That learned Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> is againſt the baptiſing of the Infants of excommunicated parents, M. <hi>Rucherf:</hi> acknowledgeth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</hi> plea. Page 176.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If then I fall in this point, I ſhall fall with excellent men, M. <hi>Cartwright,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52370:23"/>Hooker, Cotton</hi> and others of our <hi>N. E.</hi> Divines, and others (it is likely) whom I know not.</p>
            <p>Generall rules ſtand, when we have ſuch a particular caſe (as you menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, p. 13.) falls our, we ſhall conſider it, I give you no caſes but ſuch as have really beene.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed further, I muſt have recourſe to your <hi>Diatr.</hi> with Mr. <hi>Hocker</hi> for another way of admitting children to Baptiſme, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Suretiſhip:</hi> for this is one of my errours <hi>that I ſuppoſe the next parent onely can give the title to Baptiſme:</hi> and this was Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> errour as well as mine; you tell us two other wayes: 1. The <hi>remoter parents</hi> [which I have diſpatched, if it can be proved by better grounds then yet you have brought, yet it hurts not me nor Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> the queſtions ſtand firme ſtill as we handle them:] The 2. is <hi>Adoption</hi> or <hi>Suretiſhip,</hi> ſo that you give three or rather foure wayes how children may come to Baptiſme; for <hi>Adoption</hi> and <hi>Sur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſhip,</hi> I conceive differ very much. Yet theſe ſhall not hinder me nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no more then Mr. <hi>Hocker,</hi> though you can prove them, if you will let them be perſons rightly qualified for Church members, who do <hi>Adops.</hi> &amp;c. and by vertue of whom the child is baptiſed, ſo that I could eaſe my ſelfe that way: I like not this ſo well as the former. I will turn to <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Where we will obſerve who were to be circumciſed, 1. <hi>Abraham,</hi> 2. his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſeed, 3. his ſervants then in his familie, whom he had taught the way of Jehovah,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſw.</hi> 17. Gen. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and who ſhould ſeeme by faith to obey ſo hard a precept, their children alſo if they had any borne in the houſe. So after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe who were bought with money, which I conceive were only ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, theſe we finde in this <hi>chap.</hi> here then (under favour) <hi>I</hi> finde no Adoption, which I conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive is, <hi>the taking of a ſtranger, or one who is not of our naturall ſeed, into the ſtate of filiation.</hi> But that <hi>Abraham,</hi> or the J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wes afterwards, tooke the children of Heathens into a <hi>ſtate of filiation,</hi> I finde no ſuch thing: I queſtion much whether the Jewes could doe as we doe in Adopting make ſuch our Heires; they could not I doubt give any of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> away to a Heathen, though they were Adopted, of which I finde no footſteps. <hi>To ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Adopted other Jewes children, and ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed them,</hi> this is vaine. Hence then I conceive if we cleave to the chapter, baptiſing by Adoption cannot be proved, becauſe there was no circumciſing by Adoption.</p>
            <p>If it be objected; <hi>If thoſe who were bought, if ſervants might be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, then thoſe who are Adopted may be Baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray let us make no Syllogiſmes for firſt inſtitutions; had Adoption there beene mentioned, and by vertue of that Circumciſion adminiſtred, then the argument had beene fairer to prove baptining by Adoption; but there appeares no ſuch thing in the firſt Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>If you will take liberty to make Inſtitutions by ſyllogiſmes, we ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a gap quickly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This way of Adoption will ſeldome trouble us, for it is ſo rare a thing that I never as yet knew one that was thus Adopted, I have heard of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52370:23"/>one, who alſo had his name changed, and inherited Lands, but I knew him not; I know ſuch as have no children, and they have been offered children, but they would never accept any.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which is yet rarer, I never heard of any that did adopt children whilſt they were Infants, but when grown up, ſo as they tooke liking of their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and carriage; and ſure it they came once to that, they ſhould be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted before baptiſed.</p>
            <p>But howe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this troubles me not if you can prove it, if all thoſe who are children of ſuch parents, as the queſtion men ions, muſt come to be baptiſed by Adoption, ſome p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſons ſhall have children e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p>But for ſervants there the text is cleare, only whether it will hold under the Goſpel? that is a queſtion.</p>
            <p>Give me leave humbly to propound my thoughts, I conceive that might be peculiar to that Church of the Jewes, who were the onely Church God had upon the earth, all the world beſides them being ſhut out as ſo many Dogges, not allowed any meanes to enlighten them in the knowledge of God, but onely the Book of the Creature, Chriſt not allowing his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſo much as to go into their way to preach unto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pareus</hi> tells us of a Jew that called him <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>land Gentile</hi> as he he was paſſing by him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29.</note> till the wall was broken downe; yet in that time the poore Gentiles had this priviledge, if they would become ſervants to the Jews, they might be admitted to the Seal of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>But when as the partition wall was broken downe, and Miniſters ſent out to preach to the whole world; now the Covenant was as free for the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntiles as the Jewes, <hi>teach and baptiſe,</hi> you may go into <hi>Turky, India,</hi> where you will, there is no wall to binder you: ſo now that which was the ground of that adminiſtration being taken away, that to me ſeemes to ceaſe. This alſo moves me to think ſo, becauſe in the New Teſtament, after the wall was broken downe, we finde no mention of any ſuch thing whence we ſhould ground this practiſe; for children of Believers we finde ground e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: if I did not ſee more for that in the New Teſtament then for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, I ſhould be very much ſhaken for Infant baptiſme.</p>
            <p>You ground is this: <hi>It was ſo then for Circumciſion</hi> Ergo, <hi>now for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Your Conſequence you prove, becauſe priviledges are not ſtraitned under the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. had God after Chriſt taken one Nation (ſuppoſe <hi>England,</hi> as then <hi>Canaan</hi>) and tyed up his Church to ſuch a nation, ſo that no other people could partake in the O dinances but by joyning to <hi>England,</hi> then the argument had beene good, for ſtill here had beene a wall which ſhut out the other nations, which was the ground of that Adminiſtration; but now the Church may be any where.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God hath recompenced that priviledge <hi>with a wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe</hi> I think when he ſends his Goſpel to all the world, which before was tyed up to little <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If this ſtill hold, then let the vileſt monſter in <hi>England</hi> [I have ſeene
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52370:24"/>ſuch ſtand for ſureties in former times when that cuſtome was uſed, that the <hi>Indians</hi> are honeſt men in compariſon of them] bring a ſervant which he hath bought, and become ſurety for (ſo ignorant the man is that hee had neede be carechiſed himſelfe) let him bring ſuch a one to godly M. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> (if ſuch a villaine lived in his pariſh) and bid Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at</hi> baptiſe him, as he is his ſervant, would you doe it? you muſt doe it according to that text, for when they were Apoſtatiz'd they did, no queſtion, circumciſe them if they tooke them: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a villaine be excommunicated, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gives title alſo for ought I can diſcerne by you, for though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es were excommunicated, yet I ſee by your doctrine they might circumciſe ſuch.</p>
            <p>To ſay no, <hi>I would have ſuch as are underſtanding and godly men only, (or not ſcandalous) who do undertake for them, able to inſtruct them,</hi> &amp;c. Sir, you have nothing in the text for any ſuch thing; beſides if you can prove it, you hurt not my queſtion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I obſerve a vaſt difference betweene their ſervants and ours, they had ſtrong power over their ſervants, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.20, 21. I obſerved in <hi>New En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> the <hi>Indians</hi> whom we had taken in warre, or others who lived with us ſometimes halfe or a whole yeare, yet if they could handſomly get away from us they would, and did; we ſhould have done finely to have bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them; we buy no ſervants who are Engliſh men, or Chriſtians, as you call them, to be under our power as they were. Hence learned <hi>Rives</hi> ſaith, <hi>there bad ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de be a great caution leſt the Ordinance be prophaned, for our ſervants are not as theirs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Gen. 17. p. 443. laſt Ed. <hi>To.</hi> 4. l. 5. c. 11. ſ. 2.</note> And lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned <hi>Chamier</hi> ſpeakes very warily upon the queſtion: <hi>Servi ſi fim verè ſervi quales olim, non diffitear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nam Abrahamo legimus imperatum ut circumcideret ſuos omnes ſervos, ſed quales hodià not ſerves babem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ut plurimum quia verè liberi ſuns, non putem ſic tractandus, non cor quidem qui jure belli fiunt ſubditi principibus, nam hoc genus ſubditorum tamen liberum manet: De natu ergo ex parentibus inſidelibus liberis, ſi conſentiant parentes, diſtinguendum putem: Conſentiunt enim vel ip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i facti fideles, ac tune nulla difficultas,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>vel perſeverates in infidelitate, ac tum non putem baptizandor,</hi> &amp;c. For thoſe who are <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rè ſervi</hi> which it ſeemes we have none, but if we had ſuch, ſhould we baptiſe them being <hi>adulti</hi> before they be <hi>taught</hi> the Covenant, and ſee if they will owne it? <hi>Teach and Baptize;</hi> for Infants, I thinke we never buy ſuch ſervants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For ſuretiſhip that comes not in this way by being bought as they were, I have nothing to ſay to it, if you can prove it to be a divine Inſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I will attend to it, but I think it will prove but an humane Invention; for ſureties being joyned with parents,<note place="margin">Caranz <hi>p. 17.</hi> Pet. Mart. lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. com. <hi>822.</hi>
               </note> we know who was the parent of that invention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Higin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was no Apoſtle: if you have a better parent for your ſureti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip I pray bring him forth.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if any man hath a minde to be a ſurety for other folkes children let him, <hi>per me lices.</hi> I thinke thoſe who have children of their owne, and know what is to educate them, will not be forward to be ſureties for others: I doubt many men if they examine how they have diſcharged their ſureti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52370:24"/>heretofore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, have cauſe to be humbled, for I thinke moſt never regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it; and how to diſcharge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t when they have them not under their charge, and remove ſo commonly as we do, I know not.</p>
            <p>But you with tell me of the ſtream of Divines are for it; there is a little <hi>Rivules</hi> that is not acknowledged by <hi>Gerhard, loc. co. To.</hi> 4. p. 583. he quotes <hi>Galvin, Beza, Bucanus;</hi> and for <hi>Beza, Walaeus</hi> doth acknowledge, <hi>tutius judicat ut priuserudiantur. Hunnius</hi> alſo, <hi>Rivet, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith</hi> is againſt it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>To.</hi> 1. p. 492. on Gen. 17. p. 343. <hi>de bapt.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Let me adde one more of no ſmall note, <hi>Tertullian</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>veniant dum adoleſcunt, veniant dum diſcunt,</hi> which words you muſt either under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand as ſome doe againſt Infant-baptiſme altogether, as divers doe, ſaith <hi>Lauren.</hi> upon <hi>Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tul.</hi> and conclude from hence, and a place of <hi>Nazian. Orat. in San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Lavac.</hi> that theſe two Fathers were againſt Infant-baptiſm [though I think <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaks enough in that Ocation to cleare his minde] or if you will not rake it ſo, you muſt take it that <hi>Tertullian</hi> there ſpeaks againſt baptiſing by ſureties, and he that reads two lines before ſhall eaſily perceive that is his meaning; and ſo Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> interpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s him, and that clearely:<note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Tombs</hi> p. 36.</note> ſo then you have not all on your ſide. So much for your way of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption.</p>
            <p>Now I returne to your anſwer;<note place="margin">Page 15.</note> p. 15. <hi>you tell me there I have ſtarted a new queſtion:</hi> Sir, you know I ſaid at the firſt, I muſt move two queſtions, and for this had I not moved it, I had ſaid nothing, for what if I had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that it is onely the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt parent gives right to Baptiſme? yet if ſuch pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents as theſe in the Q. were judged fit Church members, and ſo fit to give title, I had ſaid nothing, that therefore was my ſcope to prove theſe were not fit, and conſequently ought to be reformed, or ſhut out of the Church; of which before.</p>
            <p>You ſay not much to my firſt Argument to prove they are not,<note place="margin">Page 16.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not <hi>viſible Saints;</hi> you <hi>acknowledge they are not, nor ought to be admitted, if now they were to be admitted:</hi> then reforme ſuch, or caſt them out: for that you ſay of <hi>Corinth,</hi> I ſay it is no wonder though <hi>Paul</hi> call the whole Church <hi>Saints,</hi> making denomination from the <hi>melior,</hi> and it is likely the <hi>Major</hi> part, as <hi>viſible Saints:</hi> but had they beene all ſuch as you ſay, groſly ignorant, or ſcandalous, whether the Apoſtle would then have called them Saints or no I cannot tell.</p>
            <p>What you ſay about profeſſion of faith that is requiſite to give a man admiſſion, I have elted it before p. 1. you ſay preſently:<note place="margin">Page 17.</note> 
               <hi>This is ſufficient for admiſſion, but as there muſt he more to, continue ſuch in the Church,</hi> &amp;c. you ſay p. 19. <hi>more is required to firſt admiſſion, then to continuance in the Church.</hi> I know not how to reconcile theſe.</p>
            <p>For <hi>poſitive</hi> matter for Excommuncation, you ſay right, there muſt be ſo indeed, and I think we are not to ſeek for that: but for Excommunication I gave you my thoughts before.</p>
            <p>For my ſecond Argument <hi>that falls you ſay alſo:</hi> I doe not know that my firſt is fallen yet, for you have yeilded the Argument. I pray what is the queſtion? I muſt ſet it downe becauſe of theſe two anſwers
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52370:25"/>you give to my two next Arguments, which you mightily contemne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They doe but ſay they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, when whole converſation manifeſts the contrary.</note> The Q. is, <hi>Whether is this bare profeſſion of ſaith in Christ</hi> [for thouſands in England doe but barely ſay it, that they beleeve in him, they know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Faith, nor of Chriſt, only the Name, ſuch a one their Father; or ſome body told them of, I gave you ſome inſtances before] <hi>though parents be groſsely ignorant, ſcandulous, and refuſe to ſubject to Church Diſcipline, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make a man, and continue him a Member of the viſible Church?</hi> The firſt Argument ſtands as yet.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Argument was this, <q>If this bare profeſſion be ſufficient, then nonen can be caſt out for the vileſt ſins, Hereſie, &amp;c. becauſe he is the ſame now as when he was admitted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You anſwer, <hi>The conſequence is unſound, and the proofe like it</hi> [you are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nimble methinks, but why ſo unſound?] <hi>for when he was firſt admitted upon his</hi> profeſſion, <hi>no ſuch ſcandall appeared, but now it doth, there he is not the ſame that he was, when admitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, by <hi>profeſſion</hi> you either meane ſuch a <hi>profeſſion,</hi> as you have mentioned above in this page, as I thinke you doe, and ſo you ſpeake not <hi>ad idem;</hi> or if you meane ſuch a <hi>profeſſion</hi> as the queſtion ſtared mentions, then Sir it is not ſo, for either groſſe ignora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, or ſcandall did appeare, unleſſe you meane that juſt at that time when he came to you and told you he did believe in Chriſt, be did not manifeſt any ſcand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll to you; was not <hi>drunke,</hi> or did not <hi>ſweare,</hi> or ſhew <hi>uncleanneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. juſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that time: for ſo thoſe who come to require Baptiſme for their children, doe not come drunk, or ſweare. &amp;c. in that very inſtant time, but before they cameth y would, and when the child is baptiſed, can ſweare, &amp;c. and its well if divers be not drunk, if they have boone companions to joyne with; ſome have been little better. So that for all your haſt, the Argument is ſound enought, but ſo is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Anſwer.</p>
            <p>The third Argument you ſay <hi>is like the former, very weake:</hi> I pray leave out ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and let <hi>weake</hi> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nought, it is poſſible it will not prove <hi>weak.</hi> What is the Argument?</p>
            <p>A Rebell oppoſing Chriſt in his viſible Kingdome is not fit to be a Member of it, becauſe no ſubject.</p>
            <p>You anſwer, <hi>be is not fit to be admitted if no Member before:</hi> Sir, what is the Q. <hi>whether is ſuch a bare profeſſion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>fit to make,</hi> &amp;c. to <hi>make</hi> a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? then this is not ſit your pen hath affirmed: but then the Argument is not <hi>very weake,</hi> but <hi>very ſtrong</hi> to prove one part of the queſtion, your ſelfe acknowledge it in your firſt words, and ſo you have done before, p. 16. [but ſay you, <hi>he is fit to be continued till tryall of Reformation be paſt:</hi>] Sir you ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove in this page, <hi>that a bare profeſsion with the mouth that he believes in Jeſus Chriſt, though viſibly he lives like an Infidell, is not ſufficient to qualifie a man to be</hi> made <hi>or</hi> continued <hi>a Member.</hi> The queſtion ſpeaks of ſuch a bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; if you will ſay a moral converſation, though groſly ignorant, will ſarve the turne, there hath beene as good, and now are among Infidels,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52370:25"/>and thoſe who doe profeſſe Chriſt, for drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, &amp;c. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, lying, ſtealing, diſobedience to parents, when growne up, &amp;c. are as bad and worſe then Infidels, <hi>Indians</hi> will ſhame them, ſo that the <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> of his <hi>profeſston</hi> is not that which doth continue him a Church men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but the Churches continuance, or impotency if the Church went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to reforme and could not, as in the time of the Hierarchie; if it be the <hi>ſufficiency of his profeſsion</hi> keepes him in, for ought I know you may let him alone when power is in your hand to caſt him out.</p>
            <p>Moſt of this page is ſpoken to before,<note place="margin">Page 18.</note> only to two propoſitions (as you call them) of mine.</p>
            <p>You anſwer: <q>That which conſtitutes a Church, continues a Church; if then a bare profeſſion be not ſufficient to make a Member, nor is it enough to continue a man a Member of a Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You anſwer, <hi>both Propoſitions are faulty: the</hi> Minor, <hi>for we have proved that a profeſsion of faith, nothing appearing to the contrary, will conſtitute a Member, and ſo a Church of many Members though all Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, the <hi>profeſsion of faith</hi> you ſpeake of here, is not the <hi>profeſsion of faith</hi> the queſtion ſpeaks of, for the queſtion ſpeakes of ſuch a <hi>profeſsion</hi> as hath groſſe ignorance, or open ſcandall appeating, therefore you ſpeak not <hi>ad idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all <hi>Hypocriter:</hi> there is (as M. <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wright ſaith</hi>) difference between <hi>Tares</hi> and <hi>Acorns, Goats</hi> and <hi>Swine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Major <hi>is faulty,</hi> ſay you, <hi>becauſe more is required to a</hi> firſt Admiſſion,<note place="margin">Page 19.</note> 
               <hi>then to</hi> a Continuance <hi>in the Church, as is evident in men of yeares converted from Infidels; a perſonall profeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of faith is neceſſary to ſuch, but their children are admitted and continued without it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, you ſhould have proved that more is required to the <hi>Admiſſion</hi> then the <hi>Continuance</hi> of the ſame perſon: ſpeake <hi>ad idem,</hi> there ſhould ſeeme rather that more is required to <hi>Continuance</hi> then <hi>Admiſsion,</hi> for being lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger under means he ſhould have attained more in that time, then he had when firſt admitted. <hi>You ſay children are</hi> admitted <hi>and continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d without</hi> perſonall <hi>profeſſion:</hi> I grant it, but <hi>admitted</hi> it ſeemes they are, and ſurely that is, becauſe they are reputed in the parents for viſible Saints,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. but now, Holy.</note> ſit matter for a Church, let them <hi>continue</hi> ſuch as they were reputed to be at their admiſſion and it is well enough, no more ſhall be required. Or it there be any difference it is this, more is required to their <hi>continuance:</hi> for they to their <hi>admiſſion,</hi> were required to be but viſible Saints by vertue of their parents, reputed ſuch for their ſakes, but for their <hi>continuance</hi> they muſt when growne up manifeſt <hi>actually</hi> they are ſuch, or elſe be caſt out: ſo more is required for <hi>Continuance</hi> then <hi>Admiſsion,</hi> and ſo your propoſition is falſe.</p>
            <p>For your laſt clauſe in that Paragraph, <hi>[there is another way to reforme a conſtituted Church but corrupted, then firſt to conſtitute a Church,</hi> viz. <hi>Diſcipline]</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52370:26"/>I know not what ſenſe to make of it, I ſuppoſed there was ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our in the Printer, but I finde no <hi>Errata</hi> printed, and ſo cannot tell what to ſay to it: I ſaid let Diſcipline be exerciſed, and ſo the Churches reduced to their firſt conſtitution, <hi>viz.</hi> to be ſuch as Churches ought to be. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>perceive your next heads are to oppoſe this, <hi>you have no Government ſettled;</hi> you may have it if you will, as I ſaid before, <hi>parties refuſe to ſubmit to it, ſay you,</hi> then I am the ſtronger; for if there be no Excommunication, I am not tyed to baptiſe till they be excommunicated, which you urge ſo much.</p>
            <p>You aske me agains, <hi>would I have ſuch ſuddainly ejected?</hi> why Sir is there no Church-Diſcipline but Excommunication? we uſe unleſſe offences he very notorius (and we have enough ſuch) firſt to admoniſh perſons ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to bring perſons to repentance; if that will not doe, we ſuſpend; if that will not doe,<note place="margin">So ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive non-Communion to be an Act of Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note> then excommunicate. <hi>I</hi> ſaid before, the times we now are caſt in are to be conſidered, as the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyden Profoſſours</hi> ſpeake in the ſame caſe, but becauſe you cannot excommunicate you will doe nothing: and when you have excommunicated it is all one with you, ſo that you doe but delude us. I doe not abſolutely deny any Baptiſme, but conditionally if they will not come to be inſtructed, and give us ſome better teſtimony of their converſation: but before they will be catchiſed by me, and give any better teſtimony they will fling away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now ſay you all his argumet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will be caſily diſſolved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 20.</note> its well. What you have ſpoken to in this page 20. I have anſwered before; onely where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you ſay, <hi>I have</hi> often <hi>confeſſed that perſons tolerated ought not to bro excluded the Lords Supper.</hi> Sir, I will keepe to the title of my Booke, it ſhall be <hi>A Sober Reply,</hi> and I ſay, I have not <hi>once</hi> ſaid any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>But then you call to Miniſters to examine <hi>whether they have done well in excluding halfe (it may bee) of their Pariſh from the Supper by their owns power alone.</hi> And page 26.28. you ſeeme to condemne this practiſe; ô brave Reformation! in the Biſhops time a Miniſter alone made no queſtion to doe this; and now every Miniſter is a Biſhop, as I am ſure you will grant, that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> is all one; yet now Miniſters muſt not doe it, but let all come to the Supper, till a <hi>Glaſſis</hi> be ſet up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here you tell us we cry out againe, and call people to ſeparate from you becauſe you want an Ordinance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 21.</note> then adde, <hi>The Lord judge betweene us in this matter:</hi> this ſentence you uſe alſo in your other book, but <hi>I</hi> pray apply it to thoſe who ſo call for ſeparation from you, my conſcience cleares me from any ſuch thing: therefore Sir doe you not uſe ſuch a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vainely.</p>
            <p>Then you come to anſwer the weak Argument:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Such as the queſtion mentions, <hi>dejure</hi> ought, and <hi>de facto</hi> pre excluded from the Lords ſupper, <hi>Ergo,</hi> ought alſo to be excluded from their Infants Baptiſme.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This you ſay you deny with all the proofes of is, the Proofe is as weake as the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52370:26"/>conſequence,</hi> viz. <q>Becauſe Baptiſme ſeales to the ſame Govenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Lords Supper doth. <hi>Ergo,</hi> if excluded from one Seale, then from the other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The proof againe is like to the formar,</hi> viz. <q>Becauſe ſuch perſons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare peare not to be thoſe to whom the Seal of the Lords Supper doth belong, having no right in thoſe priviledges; therefore Baptiſme ſignifying and fealing as great priviledges as the Lords Supper, they cannot convey a title unto that Seale for their children, but ought to be excluded.</q>
            </p>
            <p>All is weake that Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> oppoſes; there are in Logick thoſe wayes of anſwering, which Logicians call <hi>Solutiones apparcutes,</hi> one of them is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this you are well acquainted with, to ſlight the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments brought againſt you, tell your Reader they are <hi>weak;</hi> and thats halfe and anſwer at leaſt.</p>
            <p>All are not of your minde concerning this Argument:<note place="margin">His Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of free Admiſſ. to L. Sup. p. 24.</note> Mr. <hi>Humphries</hi> ſaith, <hi>thoſe who have gone about to anſwer this, bad better happily ſaid nothing, for our free courſe of baptiſme, and a deny all of this is ſuch a Seam-rent as will never be hanſomly drawns up, though ſtitchs together.</hi> For his judgment in Admiſſion of all to Lords Supper I leave it.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee how weak you ſhew it: your anſwer is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Argument ought to procced of the ſame perſons,</hi> viz. <hi>ſuch as ought to be excluded from the Lords Supper, ought (if now they were to be baptiſed) alſo to be excluded from Baptiſme for themſelves: but this doth not reach the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for they being borne Chriſtians, of Chriſtians have right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Sir, have you catched me in that fallacy, I have taken you ſo often in? I hope not: I have ſpoken before to this, the title of the parents and the children is but one and the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I doubt not but Maſter <hi>Cawdrey</hi> conceives there are thouſands in <hi>England</hi> that <hi>dejure</hi> ought to be excluded the Lords Supper, elſe be muſt condemne the Aſſembly for injudicious men that ſhould trouble the Parliament for an Act, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe Mr. <hi>Caws</hi> yeilds, were they now to be baptiſed ought not to be baptiſed, the argument proceeds cleare againſt them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet the children of ſuch parents being bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Chriſtians, of ſuch Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as ought not to be baptiſed themſelves (if they were not baptiſed) theſe may: which is ſtrange to me, that children which have their title becauſe borne of ſuch parents they may be baptiſed, but the parents themſelves who give the title, muſt not:</p>
            <p>Therefore I reply, if the argument proceeds ſo ſtrongly againſt the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents themſelves, then much more againſt the children, for If may ſelfe who muſt have title firſt for my ſelfe, and then for my child, ought to be denyed it, then much more my child, whoſe title is mine, and depends wholly upon me for it: for this I conceive to be a ſound truth, if a perſon have ten or twenty children, and theſe be baptiſed becauſe Chriſtians, born of ſuch a parent, then I doe twenty times juſtifie that the parent from whom
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52370:27"/>theſe children proceed, have right and title to Baptiſme. So that which you ſay is not a ſound aſſertion, p. 24. (which how it came under the third argument I know not, for it belongs to the firſt,) <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>If I can give the child one Seale of the Covenant by vertue of the parent, I will give the parent the other, I think is a very ſound aſſertion, it never troubled me as yet.</q> But what makes it ſo? ſay you, <hi>I may ſee reaſon to deny the parent the Lords Supper, and yet baptiſe his child, becauſe more is required of the one then the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the child I require nothing of it, but looke to the parent from whom it derives its tith, if you require any thing of me, ſaith the child, goe to my parent from whom I deſcended: why then doe you ſay, <hi>you require more of the one, then the other?</hi> neither 2. doe I ſee what more you are to require of a perſon to admit him to the Lords Supper, then his child to baptiſme: If a perſon doe viſibly appeare to have the condition of the Covenant, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Church-member, how you can deny him the Lords Supper I know not: ſo for baptiſme. If there were two conditions of the Covenant of grace, and that Baptiſme reſpected one, and the Lords Supper the other, then there might be ſome eaſon, why the Church ſhould looke to one more then another, but I know but of one condition.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 21.</note> You ſay moreover: <hi>The young children of members are unfit to be admitted to the Lords Supper, yet not to be excluded from Baptiſme, The reaſon is becauſe more is required to the Lords Supper, then to their Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſay: 1. If children did as much depend on their parents for the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> as they doe for Baptiſme, then for ought I know, they may have (as was the old cuſtome) the Lords Supper, as Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſhould have proved that leſſe is to be required of thoſe who doe give them title to their Baptiſme, then for themſelves to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 22.</note> So that whereas you ſay, <hi>all my falſe conſequences are grounded upon my firſt (falſe) premiſed ſuppoſition,</hi> viz. [<hi>That the child hath no right but in relation to the</hi> next <hi>parent</hi>] (the word <hi>next</hi> (by your favour) was not there put in,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I may conſider the Parent and Child, as,</hi> argumentum primum &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum <hi>in Logick:</hi> primum babet arguendi vim in ſe, &amp; à ſe: ortum in ſe ſed non à ſe. <hi>Its but deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </note>,) ſo I ſay your anſwer to this argument, runs upon a falſe ſuppoſition, <hi>viz. that children are baptized by vertue of a title diſtinct from their parents,</hi> If you can prove that, <hi>viz.</hi> that the parent requires baptiſme for himſelfe by one title, and the child by another title diſtinct from his, then your anſwer will be ſtrong; elſe it is as weake and weaker then the argument, which you ſo much ſlight: for the reſt of your anſwer, I have ſpoken to it before, and therefore repeace nothing <hi>for the examples of Scripture or Hiſtory:</hi> will you doe nothing but what you have example for? is not argument drawne from Scripture-grounds ſufficient for me, though there be not examples ſet downe? For the <hi>perſonall default</hi> I have ſpoken to it before.</p>
            <p>For my <hi>Dilemma</hi> which you would turne upon me, I ſee you take that for granted which I have not yeilded, therefore my <hi>Dilemma</hi> ſtands as it did before againſt you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 23.</note> For my <hi>Querie (Whether the child may not be ſuſpended in caſe the parent he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52370:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuſpended continuing obſtinate)</hi> you would anſwer me out of principles which are not mine: I pray prove, <hi>that juspenſion is an Ordinance inſtituted onely with respect to the Lords Supper.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">Being it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Divines <hi>Excommunicatio Minor.</hi>
               </note> prove that the caſe now ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us as now it doth, in beginning of Reformation, wee may not deny the <hi>ſigna gratiae</hi> as the <hi>Layden profeſſors</hi> ſay, though by reaſon of the multitude we cannot proceed to Excommunication. 3. Why may we not proceed to non-communion?</p>
            <p>My ſecond Argument was this.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Such Parents if now they were to be Baptized, ought not to be Baptized, <hi>Ergo,</hi> they cannot challenge it for their Children: Baptiſme belongs primatily to the Parent.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You againe deny the conſequence and the prooſe of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt you ſay: <hi>It is a received</hi> maxime <hi>amongſt the Lawyers,</hi> quod fieri non debuit, factum valet: <hi>Suppoſe an unfit perſon Baptized, his Baptiſme is not null, be is a Member till legally exeluded, and ſo hath right for himſelfe and his to be conſequent Priviledges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence firſt thoſe Indians whom the Fryars Baptized in the Weſt Indies without inſtruction,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heylen. Geog.</hi> P. 773.</note> have right and title for themſelves and theirs to all Church priviledges. The perſons were unfit who were Baptized I an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> yet ſaith Mr. <hi>Ca.</hi> unfitneſſe doth not debarre, till excluded. No nor then neither. Let others doe as thoſe <hi>Fryars</hi> did, yet this Argument holdes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this anſwer earrieth it, <hi>That Baptiſme makes a Member of a viſible Church:</hi> obſerve his words, <hi>ſuppoſe an unfit perſon Baptized,</hi>
               <note place="margin">If unfit to be Baptized, then unfit to be a Member.</note> 
               <hi>his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is not null, be is a Member:</hi> which way came this man to be a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? not by his Chriſtianity, (which you uſe to ſay) for he is a <hi>perſon unfit</hi> you ſay: but his Baptiſme made him thus, which is</p>
            <p>Firſt, croſſe to your own propoſition: <hi>Review</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hoo.</hi> P. 94. <hi>Baptiſme doth not make a man a Member of a Church</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if Baptiſme doth make a Member, and conſequently gives <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the title to his Childs Baptiſme, Then <hi>Conſtantine, Valentinianes,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe who deferred their Baptiſme, were ſo long no Members of the Church, nor could give title to their Childrens Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Primum in unoquoque genere eſt meuſura aliorion:</hi> ſo take the firſt in <hi>genere Baptizatorum,</hi> what was the cauſe of their Baptizing; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> cauſe they hearing of the word <hi>Taught, Believed,</hi> and <hi>joyned to the Church;</hi> it was not becauſe any other was Baptized, ſo the ſame holds now, a perſon being reputed <hi>a Believer</hi> and a Church-member [whether in the Parents or otherwiſe] this is the ground of its Baptiſme; then it is not anothers being Baptized that is the ground of my Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the ground of the ſealing of the Covenant, is becauſe the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> perſon appeares to be in Covenant, not becauſe it was firſt ſealed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Child is looked upon within the Covenant by reaſon of the Parent, as was <hi>I ſhmael</hi> before <hi>Abraham</hi> was circumciſed, if in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52370:28"/>then (ſay you) the child is a Church-member: then it is not the Parents being Baptized that gives the title. Hence your Notion in the ſame Page 23. <hi>[If the Parents ſin did annull his own Baptiſme, it were a queſtion whether it did not hinder his childes Baptiſme]</hi> which alſo implies it is the Parents Baptiſme that is the cauſe of his childes Baptiſme] comes to nothing.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond anſwer, is from none of my Principles.</p>
            <p>Your third I have ſpoken to alſo. <hi>I did not expreſſe excommunication as a qualification in the queſtions</hi> it is true, I have ſpoken to this alſo before.</p>
            <p>What you have ſaid to the third Argument, I have alſo ſpoken to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my fourth Argument ran thus: <q>[To give the ſeale of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace to a child by vertue of one who appeares to be in covenant with the Devill, is a prophaning of the Ordinance.]</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this you anſwer foure wayes, the laſt I have ſpoken to, but not the other three, which I will conſider.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 25.</note> Firſt, <hi>you deny that ſuch perſons as the</hi> Q. <hi>memions are viſibly in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Satan, eſpecially if tolerated, for ſo long they are viſibly in the externall covenant of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What you meane by this <hi>Externall Covenant</hi> of the Church I cannot imagine: not <hi>Baptiſme</hi> I hope; nor the <hi>Externall Church covenant</hi> wee ſpeake of, and you ſo much oppoſe; for the Covenant of grace, they are not viſibly under that: there needs no Covenant <hi>formally</hi> betweene the Devill and us, naturally hee hath us ſtrong enough though wee make <hi>no formall</hi> Covenants with him. But when are men ſaid to be under the Covenant of Grace? is it not when they,
<list>
                  <item>1. Seeke to underſtand it,</item>
                  <item>2. Chooſe it as their greateſt joy and portion,</item>
                  <item>3. Rejoyce in nothing ſo as when under the power of it,</item>
                  <item>4. When will not endure to be drawne from under the Dominion of it, but their hearts ſinke with ſorrow when the old man rebells againſt it,</item>
                  <item>5. When externally their Converſation anſwers it,</item>
                  <item>6. When delight in thoſe who are in Covenant with themſelves alſo, &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
Turne it now, when perſons care not for underſtanding of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but they are wiſe in wayes of ſinne, chooſe thoſe wayes, their joy is when they are in the enjoyment of ſuch wayes, cannot endure to be pulled off from them, but troubled when ſtopped in their courſe, viſibly thus they walke in their courſe, and chooſe ſuch for their companions, what ſhall wee judge of theſe? What ever <hi>Covenant</hi> you meane, I am ſure they are not under that Covenant viſibly, of which Baptiſme is a Seale.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Secondly, you ſay, <hi>ſuppoſe a Perſon be Excommunicate, and ſo delivered unto Satan (as the incefluous Perſon was) yet it were hard to ſay he were viſibly in Covenant with Satan, though at the preſent under his Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be under a Church-cenſure, which is appointed for cure of a Perſon, is far different from the eaſe now we ſpeak of.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:52370:28"/>
            <p>That power of Satan the excommunicate perſon is under, is an afflicting power, therefore not choſen by the perſon, as is the other.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are not Excommunicated may be viſibly in Covenant with Satan in that ſenſe the Argument ſpeaks of, when one who is Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated may not be ſo, as the inceſtuous perſon repenting, and ſunke with ſorrow.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, you ſay, <hi>every groſſe ſin (as in</hi> Noah <hi>and</hi> David, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>does not</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>conclude a man viſibly in Covenant</hi> (with Satan you meane) <hi>much leſſe ignorance, as in children and youths Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay 1. If I had not reverenced your grace and Parts, I would have given you another anſwer, ſir it is ſtrange that when I in the proofe of the <hi>Minor</hi> ſaid, <hi>[A perſon whoſe courſe and Trade of Life is to live in ſin]</hi> that yet you ſhould anſwer from <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> their particular acts, repented of, &amp;c. You would make me a ſilly fellow that could not diſtinguiſh betweene the courſe of a mans life (when I expreſſed it) and a particular act.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Baptizing of Infants, I doe not conſider them as <hi>ignorant</hi> perſons, but viſible Saints with their Parents, and thoſe muſt have knowledge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How are we gone from the ignorance of the <hi>Parent,</hi> to the ignorance of the Infant?</p>
            <p>Then you come in with your <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> [ſee whither <hi>this new way leades its followers.</hi>] Yes, I pray ſee by what you have anſwered, whither it leades: I think you might have ſpared your triumphing here, unleſſe your anſwer had beene ſtronger.</p>
            <p>For my fifth Argument, <hi>the jumbling of the moſt prophane and godly in the ſame Ordinance and under the ſame Prayers:</hi> you tell me I may doe it, ſo I do <hi>but grieve,</hi> &amp;c. of this before: but fir when conſcience flies in a mans face for giving away the ſeale of the Covenant to ſuch a one, this will not quiet conſcience to tell it, Mr. <hi>Gawdrey ſaith you may do it.</hi> You know what Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> ſaid before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 26.</note> Then you come to the great Objection. The Jewes circumciſing of all. My firſt anſwer to this Objection was, <q>I would ſee a proofe that the Prieſts did debarre many from the Paſſeover, for morall uncleaneneſſe, many yeares, (as ours doe from the Supper) and yet had their children circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this you anſwer: <hi>The Prieſts are blamed for admitting the Morally uncleane to ſome Ordinances, but it concernes him to prove where ever they were blamed for circumciſing the Children of ſuch.</hi> 44. Ezek. 9.</p>
            <p>To which I ſay, 1. That Text ſpeakes of the times under the Goſpell, and it cannot be accompliſhed under the Old Teſtament, as our Annotations make it cleare, it ſpeakes of a time when circumciſion is out of date.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Circumciſion was never committed to the Prieſts as now Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52370:29"/>to the Miniſters, therefore there was no blame to them due for that point.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Since it reſpects the Goſpell, it concerns thoſe who practiſe ſo as if by <hi>Sanctuary</hi> were meant onely the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> to prove that there, where the Prieſts are blamed for bringing into the Sanctuary ſuch perſons, he meanes onely admiſſion to the Lords Supper, thoſe who interpret muſt prove. It ſhould ſeeme very faire, that <hi>Sauctuary</hi> is more then Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe thoſe who were brought into the Sanctuary might come to the Paſſeover in old time.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond anſwer is, you <hi>Question the Practice of our Miniſters, whether it can be juſtified.</hi> I ſee you are pinched, but no doubt their keeping of that holy Ordinance is juſtifiable enough.</p>
            <p>My ſecond anſwer was, [I conceived ſome thing was peculiar to <hi>that</hi> Church in <hi>that</hi> Ordinance, and ſo conceive ſtill. I ſhall add ſomething more.]</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that there was no Miniſter ſeparated by God to the diſpenſing of <hi>it,</hi> as is now of Baptiſme: but <hi>Parents, Maſters, Judges, Men</hi> or <hi>Women,</hi> yea <hi>themſelve; might adminiſter it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It did not runne to his ſeed onely as <hi>Spirituall,</hi> [as doth Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme now, <hi>for onely Believers are</hi> Abrahams <hi>Seed</hi>] but to his Seed <hi>as ſuch.</hi> The ground indeed of Gods giving of the Seale of the Covenant at firſt was, becauſe of that Covenant God was in with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but this Covenant they (many of them) did never regard but reject, taking Circumciſion onely to be the Covenant, ſo being his Seed in whom they did ſo glory,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.39.44.</note> they would circumciſe their Children, though the Devill was their Father.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the nature of the Seale and Signe being an abiding Marke in the fleſh (which Baptiſme is not.) And by that they were diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Heathens by an apparent marke, it made me thinke there was ſomething God further aimed at in it, in reference to them: which I perceive <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> will ſecond me in: when <hi>Trypho</hi> had beene urging the neceſity of Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dialog. cum Tryph.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> hee anſwers him; <hi>God foreſeeing you ſhould be ſcattered, and beaten out of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thither againe, left Circumciſion a Marke in your fleſh, now by no other note can you be knowne but by your Circumciſion.</hi> This is part of his anſwer. And ſurely there ſeemes to be ſomething in it, for had it not beene for Circumciſion, in theſe many yeares they have beene ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, they might eaſily have loſt their Diſtinction from the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, at leaſt abundance of them, but by this they are knowne to this day.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This much prevailes with me to thinke ſomething was peculiar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. Thoſe who were not Circumciſed were to be <hi>Cut off</hi> Whether by the Magiſtrate, or by Excommunication, as ſaith learned
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52370:29"/>
               <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> take it how you will, will you ſay the ſame of Infants not baptiſed? muſt the Magiſtrate <hi>cut ſuch off?</hi> or ſhall the Church excommunicate all ſuch? I trow Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> will take up the Cudgels againſt you,<note place="margin">In his Sermon before the L. Major on <hi>Eaſter Monday.</hi> 1652. p. 28. 2. Ed.</note> for he is ſo farre from thinking that Churches ſhould excommunicate <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> if godly, that he chargeth that Church with <hi>Schiſme,</hi> which ſhall deny them Communion becauſe <hi>ſuch.</hi> Expound it how you will, (ſo it be true) that wil ſhew ſome difference, and argue ſomething was peculiar.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I ſaid [when the Jewes came to requite Baptiſme, it was not enough we are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, <hi>Ergo,</hi> baptiſe us, [this was enough to Circumciſion] but <hi>John</hi> requires Repentance.</p>
            <p>To this you anſwer, <hi>it was a new Ordinance, in which Repentance was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the first parents.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. But what then? though new, it was but a Seale to the ſame Covenant they were in before, and they being viſibly under the ſame Covenant, why ſhould more be required of them, if there were not ſome difference between the adminiſtrations of theſe Ordinances?</item>
                  <item>2. But was not <hi>Repentance</hi> required in Circumciſion? did not Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion note <hi>the cutting off the Old Man?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Col. ix.</note> and is that done without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? if repentance were not required there as well as in Baptiſme, you wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l confirme me the more, and weaken the arguing from Circumciſion to Baptiſme, very much in my apprehenſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. This made me to think ſo, <hi>becauſe when they fell to their foule Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, yet they Circumciſed:</hi> I pray Sir ſpeake our plainely, if one of your Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſhould ſacrifice his children to <hi>Mole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b, worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p thoſe vile and uncleane Gods,</hi> which they did, would you baptiſe his child without any more adoe?</p>
            <p>If none but ſuch as <hi>Maymony</hi> (before quoted) ſaith, ought to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, then their Circumciſion was irregular, for they threw oft <hi>Abrahams</hi> way, and his God: but if all <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> meerely according to the fleſh, had a title to Circumciſion, then it was peculiar to them, and they were regularly enough circumciſed. But this helps not us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That place <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3. the children borne of the ſtrange wives were to be put away,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ut proficiamus: vulg e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus; <hi>Vata.</hi>
               </note> as well as the ſtrange wives; its very likely they would cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe them, but yet put away: if they ought not to be circumciſed or were not, yet it will imply ſome difference.</p>
            <p>For all the reſt to p. 29. I have ſpoken to before: there after you had condemned my rigidneſſe for non-admiſſion of the children of ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, then you ſhew your Judgement, <hi>that all ought to be Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>You ſay if one Miniſter will not baptize, another will,</hi> [let others doe as they pleaſe, I muſt give account of my Stewardſhip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not his] <hi>it will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe diviſions betwixt Miniſters, by others intermedling with their charges.</hi> [I was never yet offended with any man who did Baptiſe the children of ſuch as dwell in our pariſh: I thought intermedling with other folkes charges had been no offence to the Claſſicall Government, which will excommunicate a perſon in another mans charge.]</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52370:30"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It will make the next generation, no better then Infidels being unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may prevent abundance of ſinne and ignorance, making parents looke about them, working (as experience hath proved in <hi>N. England,</hi> to reall converſion (as in charity we may judge) at leaſt to knowledge and outward conformity in divers here alſo in <hi>England,</hi> in your owne <hi>ſhire:</hi> the proofe is made, a godly miniſter that lives there told me, he will not baptiſe without a good account given him, and to this day (he told me at the Commencement) two in his pariſh were unbaptiſed; the people ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this, he told me they beſtirre themſelves to get knowledge, and give better account.</p>
            <p>This is the fruit already tried, but what then if all Miniſters did ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe unbaptiſed, Ergo Infidels,</hi> Conſtantine, Valentinianus and others, were unbaptiſed a long time, therefore they were Infidels, and <hi>Valentinianus</hi> dyed an Infidel, becauſe he dyed unbaptiſed.</p>
            <p>This will exaſperate parents you ſay.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt looke for rubs at firſt, our life is not ſuch as to have the good word and will of every body; but this daintineſſe muſt come downe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whilſt we have the civill power to ſtand by, it may be done the more caſily.</item>
               <item>2. If one of the parents give any comfortable account, it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</item>
               <item>3. Wome, their ſexe commands them more modeſty, and their educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion helps, if there be knowledge, they have advantage alſo of affections, and ſo eaſier moved upon by preaching the Word.</item>
               <item>4. For number, we ſhall find the moſt oppoſition will be in the poorer ſort, where horrible ignorance beſides prophaneneſſe abounds.</item>
               <item>5. It is but viſible Saintſhip that is required; you have ſaid enough, in my opinion, as for maintenance (which you mention) thouſands of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>England</hi> have the advantage of me, <hi>N. England</hi> voyage having bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſpoyled our Eſtates, but ordinarily Miniſters have Lands of their owne, and ſome good Glebe-Lands, wherein they are before me.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I obſerve but two things,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For what you ſay; <hi>you would have the Magiſtrate ſettle aright Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which all Congregatious ſhould be bound to ſubmit to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, you ſpeake of a hard thing, the Magiſtrate muſt needes be troubled to know which is that <hi>right</hi> Government, when there is ſo much difference among the Miniſters who call for it; one ſayes it is <hi>Claſſicall</hi> Government, another it is <hi>Congregationall,</hi> and both ſides very godly men: <hi>The Ark muſt needes ſhake when the Oxen stumble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet ſuch is the neereneſſe of the agreement between the Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and Claſſicall Government, that though one be not bound to ſubmit to the other, yet Church-government might goe on well enough, (were it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52370:30"/>not for this <hi>Separation,</hi> which will undermine both) if there were brotherly yeilding on both ſides but a little; if the peace of the Churches were as much valued as it hath been by other holy men before times, wee would not, we dare not doe as we doe.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate doth give leave for theſe two, which in reſpect of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are ſo neere, that they need not be called two; but this fearfull blaſting of the Ordinances by the ſore hand of God, and this horrible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union betweene the Congregationall and Claſſicall men, and others who are godly, ſay in my heart, there hangs a ſcourge over both Congregationall and Claſſicall men, and other profeſſours.</p>
            <p>For the reſt, p. 30. there is little to anſwer:</p>
            <p n="2">2. For your bringing in the <hi>Authority of the civill Magiſtrate, to reforme our people as Church-members;</hi> this will be poore Reformation: I thought Church-members had been <hi>formed</hi> and <hi>reformed,</hi> by the ſword of the Spirit, not of the Magiſtrate, they can ſcarce make better Lawes then they have made, for reforming of Morall vices, I think the fault lyes not in them, they cannot be Judges and Witneſſes too.</p>
            <p>For your laſt, p 31. <hi>that you would have us preſſe the conditions of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant on thoſe that we baptiſe, and that is ſufficient now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I were onely a <hi>Teacher</hi> this might ſuffice, but I thinke I am (or ſhould be) a <hi>Ruler,</hi> as well as a Teacher.</p>
            <p>If this be enough, then admit all <hi>England</hi> to the Lords Supper without ſcruple.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir I have replyed to your Booke, with as much brevity as I could; I know ſuch a man as you are will not be quiet thus, but will write againe; (I foreſee ſome things (and poſſibly you may make uſe of my Booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Separation againſt me) which I could have prevented, but upon ſome reaſons moving me I let them alone:) and it will be hard (though I am but weak) if I ſhould not ſpy out ſome things in your writing which I might oppoſe againe, but I ſee there will be no end of writing, wherefore <hi>I</hi> am reſolved to make an end; onely if I finde you bring out more ſtrength then yet I have ſeene, and that which giveth me ſatisfaction, I will returne you very hearty thanks, and publiſh it to the world that you have ſatisfied me; if not, I will be ſilent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52370:31"/>
            <head>A POST-SCRIPT <hi>To Reverend Mr.</hi> Blake.</head>
            <p>MY reply to Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi> was ready for the preſſe within ſeven weeks after his anſwer came out, but by the ill dealing of that Bookeſeller who had my Copy firſt in his hand, it comes to be thus long before it came forth: I heard not of Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> a long time after he came forth, and have poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d his booke no longer then to have but one whole day to review him, and draw up my reply, which I would have done <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but that my Bookſeller is unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to venture the charges for the printing in theſe dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. I have not read ever any more (as yet) then what concerns my ſelfe, and for his courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous handling of me without ſcorne, I kindely thanke him. I have liberty to mention but two or three things, which I ſhall doe with as much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie as I can.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. He obſerves,<note place="margin">Page 431.</note> 
                  <hi>I am diffident rather then conſident of my opinion.</hi> Sir, I did write as a man who was troubled about it, my Arguments at preſent caſting the ſcale on the negative ſide, though I had not ſuch downe weight as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired: but truly Sir I ſee nothing as yet to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e me recall my opinion, for all that is ſaid (excepting Mr. <hi>Cawdrey</hi>'s notion of <hi>Adoption</hi> in which your ſelfe are not cleare) I knew before.</item>
               <item>2. I obſerve ſometimes you dreſſe my Argument with ſuch a faſhion that I cannot know it to be mine, but diſclaime it, then you ſinde fault: p. 439. where have I mentioned the <hi>power of godlineſſe</hi> as a requiſite in him who claims Baptiſm? but to bring up a child in it is a harder matter: I have not liberty to enlarge.</item>
               <item>3. Sometimes your anſwer is a bare laying downe your owne Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with a Similitude added for illuſtration. P. 441. We now c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll for Scripture and reaſon from thence; <hi>Similia at pompam non ad pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. For my fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Argument for the negative, p. 449.450. which you ſay was Mr. <hi>Blackwoods.</hi> I never ſaw any thing of his, but I tooke it from our Brethrens practiſe, and it was that (with one thing more) which led mee into my practiſe: for when I ſaw the <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Brethren keep back half or three quarters of their Churches from the Lords Supper, and that for divers years together, yet did ſo conſtantly baptiſe their children, I thought with my ſelfe, where have theſe men a ground for this practiſe? in all the New Teſtament I could not ſinde one, nor reaſon for it, but rather againſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52370:31"/>it for the Old Teſtament, though I knew ſome were kept back for Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall uncleanneſſe from the paſſeover, yet for Moral uncleanneſſe to be kept back many yeers, and ſtill to have their children circumciſed, I found no text for that.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For Mr. <hi>Gille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>py,</hi> I have not liberty to ſet downe my thoughts.</p>
            <p>You frame your anſwer by turning my argument another way, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring me to give anſwer to your Syllogiſme: which Sir, is no clever way of diſputation; And for anſwer I need give you none,<note place="margin">Againſt the Anabap. Argu 5.</note> Mr. <hi>Iohnſon</hi> before you, and you in his words (though it may be you ſaw him not) have given a full anſwer, yet my Argument is not hurt at all, though the parent may be ſuſpended for a time, what is this to the ſuſpenſion of three parts of a Church, ſix or ten years together, and never proceed furtherr?<note n="*" place="margin">Ame Med. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el c. <hi>37. th. 22.</hi>
               </note> I would have enlarged if I might.</p>
            <p>I obſerved many other things, to which I would have replyed, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t I ſhall ſingle out onely one thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g which I will examin.<note place="margin">Goular. <hi>in 38.</hi> Ep. Cypr.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Page 4.26. <hi>Infant of Parents that are</hi> nomine tenus, <hi>Chriſtians have right to Baptiſme. If they profeſſe the worſhip of the true God, though nothing more of a Chriſtion be in them.</hi> Page 424.</p>
            <p>If by a Chriſtian <hi>nomine tenus</hi> your m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aning were, <hi>one who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but a nominall Chriſtian, as all are who are not reall,</hi> I make no queſtion but many ſuch as theſe <hi>nominall</hi> ones a Miniſter may B priſe, and their children, though they have not truth of grace in them: but I perceive you: ſcope is to ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead the word very large: and that directly oppoſite to my qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtion; <hi>If they will ſay they are Chriſtians,</hi> bene the Name of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, own his worſhip (though it be but from the cuſtome of the Nation, others do ſo, and ſo do they) though their courſe and frame of converſation be like the infidells, or worſe yet they are Chriſtians <hi>nomine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enus,</hi> hence we muſt Baptize, if they have but <hi>Fides,</hi> no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter for <hi>Obſervan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſir, I pray what if they be hereticall about the na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome of old deny the Humanity, ſome the Deity of Chriſt? what if they thinke Chriſt was a Woman (as I have given inſtance) what if they know not whether he was God or Man (as before) what if ten Gods (as before) and abundance of ſuch ſtuffe (all which yet will call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) muſt theſe be Baptized? Theſe are errors in their beliefe.</p>
            <p>But let us ſuppoſe they underſtand God and Chriſt, for their <hi>Faith</hi> they are right, but abominable in their <hi>converſation,</hi> are we now bound to Baptize becauſe of their Faith?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sir I thought Chriſtianity had taken in the <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>outward conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> as well as the <hi>bead,</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eall Chriſtian is one united to Chriſt, ſound in the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine concerning Chriſt, and wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing as Chriſt did [we ſuppoſe an old <hi>Adam</hi>]. Let him who is a <hi>nominall</hi> Chriſtian appeare live one, though he be not real, Mr. <hi>Ca</hi> will not allow him ſit, if viſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y he lives like an infidel, though he profeſſe his ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us view the Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mark</hi> 4. <hi>Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſme of Repentance;</hi> this is more then <hi>Faith: they confeſſed their ſins.</hi> v. 5. the J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s had not idolls now to confeſſe that ſin,<note place="margin">Aug. defid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2</hi> Acts op. c. <hi>8,</hi>
               </note> Doth not the ordinance note repentance alſo?</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52370:32"/>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Acts</hi> 37.38.
<list>
                  <item>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mag leb. cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 1. li. 1. cap. 10.</note> Jews, ſo had knowledge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſo ignorant as ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> believe.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, having a <hi>legall worke</hi> by the power of the Word.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, <hi>Receiving the Word.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, <hi>Repenting,</hi> they are Baptized, this is more ſtill.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Acts,</hi> Though there is not mention made of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, who were Apoſtatized from the Jews, but laid claime to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks, <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.20. expected Chriſt, v. 25. worſhipped God, <hi>Ezva.</hi> 4.2. Yet that <hi>Philip</hi> ſhould know them to be ſo abominable in converſation, and yet Baptize them, that is to be proved, ſince that others required repentance. I believe there was a more then ordinary preſence at that time, to enlighten, ſo to aw their hearts, the ſame anſwer we may give for theſe, that <hi>Auguſtin</hi> doth for the <hi>Eunuch, Bapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zavit cum Philippus, intelligi voluis impleta omnia, quae licet tacean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r in Scripturis gratia brevitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amen ſcrie traditionis ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us implenda. Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> have ſaid enough for the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> beſides <hi>Auguſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ubi prius c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and the Text is plaine.</p>
            <p>If this be not a giving <hi>Holy things to Dogs</hi> (which <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> give warning of even in Baptizing) I know not what is: Let a man be a notorious Ranter, Sodomite, Scoffer at Godlineſſe, Drunkard, no matter what this is known and proved, yet a Chriſtian <hi>nomine tenus,</hi> Therefore you muſt Baptize him.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Repentance</hi> as well as <hi>Faith</hi> was looked to in Baptizing, it appeares by the ages following the Apoſtles, for thoſe who would live in their luſts, they deferred their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aptiſme, knowing what that required. So<note n="a" place="margin">De toenit.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Ora. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nazianzen</hi> intimate, who exhort them to confeſſion of their ſinne from the example of <hi>John. Juſt. Mart. Apol.</hi> 2. is cleare for more then you mention.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Cate humeni</hi> they were ſtrict we ſee, <hi>Concil. Neocaſ. Can.</hi> 5. <hi>Concil. Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Can.</hi> 13. <hi>Concil Elib. Can.</hi> 42. a good converſation they required, thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for their long deferring I approve not that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Believer</hi> and <hi>Saint</hi> you ſay are <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nonoma's.</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> gives the reaſon, which will not help you ſir, <hi>Medul. Theo.</hi> c. 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>For the ill Members in <hi>Gorinth</hi> and <hi>Sardi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 1. Sir you muſt prove the Apoſtles knew them to be ſuch when they admitted them, and Baptized them, that they wallowed in their filth. 2. That the Churches were not too blame in letting them alone, 3. To have a <hi>Name to live,</hi> is more then you ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>For <hi>ignorance,</hi> you quote the <hi>Hebrews</hi> which I thinke hurts not me, that of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34. Is the moſt likely, but ſir do you thinke it was ſuch groſſe ignorance as I have given inſtance? was not <hi>Paul</hi> as true to his worke as <hi>Abraham</hi> or the Jews were to be in admitting to circumciſion, which you mention Page 445. I have found ſo much ignorance that the perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſhame, but yet dared not keepe from the Lords Supper, becauſe I found ſuch a worke on the heart, which ſhowed they had the thing, though could not expreſſe the thing in a definition.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52370:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>For the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lord. min J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Div.</hi> [Page 115. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and others. <hi>Gilleſ.</hi> Aar. rod. Page 482, 154, 515, 544, 555. To. 4. diſp. 4. q 3 p. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Presbyterians</hi> they have delivered their mind otherwiſe: the <hi>Fathers, Councells,</hi> and <hi>Schoolemen</hi> are of another Opinion, as appeares by <hi>Grug. de val.</hi> but I quote no more then I have read, I hope then you will pardon me though I differ. For your Anſwers to my Arguments.</p>
            <p>Your diſtinction of the word <hi>Sains</hi> I accept, and doubt not but your eyes are ſo good, that you can ſee a difference betweene a man who is but <hi>nomine ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> a Chriſtian and wallowes in his filth, and another, who walkes out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly like a Saint, though hee have not the reall qualifications of a Saint.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument muſt coſt you two lines more before it be anſwered.</p>
            <p>If a man be but <hi>Nomine tenus</hi> a Chriſtian, though never ſo abominable in his converſation, yet muſt be admitted a Member, then hee cannot be caſt out of the Church for any vile ſin, ſo long as he is <hi>nomine tenus</hi> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, he is now as he was when you admitted him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſay the Conſequence is erroneous, becauſe be did not make profeſſion of his ſin, but of his Faith,</hi> As <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it ſeemes the man muſt profeſſe his ſin with his own mouth, as his Faith, though Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> knowes he is a Ranter, &amp;c. The Members of the Church witneſſe it, yet becauſe the mans own mouth doth not profeſſe it, you admit him. Then ſir, though you know the ſame abominations after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and your Members teſtifie it, witneſſes come in, you muſt not caſt him out unleſſe he will profeſſe it. If Knowledge and Witneſſes will caſt him out (whether his mouth will profeſſe it or no) why will not the ſame keepe him out at firſt? We ſhall never find ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thinke as you ſpeake of, they will give you good words when they come to require Baptiſme, though they will ſweare and be drunk before and after in the ſame day.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> I have ſpoken to him before,<note place="margin">Aar. rod. 482.</note> and Mr. <hi>Gilleſpic</hi> anſwers for me.</p>
            <p>What is that <hi>Cenſure</hi> you would have paſſed upon a manifeſt oppoſer of Chriſt in his viſible Kingdome? he was no ſubject I ſaid, Therefore not ſit for a Church-member.</p>
            <p>But ſir I have not liberty to go further: onely this I muſt adde, I follow this diſpute with much ſadneſſe in reſpect of mine own heart: for your elſe and Mr. <hi>Ca.</hi> I honour you both, your graces, your abilities I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>knowledge are before mine, but in this point I muſt ſee more light before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yeild: as for the bond of Unity I hope (by my piece againſt the <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) you will conceive me to be one who will hold it firme with you, in this Point, I leave you to your own light, and ſhall conclude with the words of <hi>Cyprian</hi> [though ſome may ſay I am in an errour as he was] <hi>Manente concordiae vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulo, &amp; perſeverante Catholicae Eccleſiae individu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sacramento,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 52.</note> 
               <hi>actum ſuum disponit &amp; dirigit unuſquiſque Epiſcopus, ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem prep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fiti ſui Domino redditurus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:52370:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I Had but three houres liberty, and that in the night, to run over my book, and correct it, I did not obſerve many faults which would trouble the ſenſe, thoſe I leave to the Courteous Reader to correct, theſe (among others) I obſerved: Pag. 10. l. 21. r. <hi>propriè.</hi> l. 22. r. Govenant for Councell. p. 22. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undem.</hi> p. 43. for <hi>Smith</hi> r. <hi>ſaith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52370:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
